<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Paules-Crosse, vpon the 1. of Nouember, being All-Saints Day, anno 1607. By Sa: Collins, Batchelour in Diuinitie, and fellow of the Kings Colledge in Cambridge</title>
            <author>Collins, Samuel, 1576-1651.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 129 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 50 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19153</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5564</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108507</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844165</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844165</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8954</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19153)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8954)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1132:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Paules-Crosse, vpon the 1. of Nouember, being All-Saints Day, anno 1607. By Sa: Collins, Batchelour in Diuinitie, and fellow of the Kings Colledge in Cambridge</title>
                  <author>Collins, Samuel, 1576-1651.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 91, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Humfrey Lownes, for Richard Bonian, dwelling at the signe of the spread Eagle, right ouer against the great north dore of S. Pauls Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8954:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8954:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> SERMON PREACHED AT PAVLES-CROSSE, VP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON THE 1. OF NOVEMBER, BEING ALL-SAINTS DAY, ANNO 1607.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Sa: Collins,</hi> Batchelour in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie, and fellow of the Kings Colledge in Cambridge.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>LVC. 7.35.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Wiſedome is iustified of all her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>GREG. MAG. in Ezechiel.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Nihil ad defendendum honestate tutius: ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil ad dicendum veritate facilius.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Humfrey Lownes,</hi> for <hi>Richard Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> dwelling at the ſigne of the ſpread Eagle, right ouer againſt the great North dore of S. Pauls Church. 1607.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:8954:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8954:2"/>
            <head>To the moſt Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father in God, <hi>Richard,</hi> the Lord Archbiſhop of Canterburie his Grace, Primate and Metropolitane of all England, one of his <hi>Maiesties</hi> moſt honourable Priuie Councell.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie of the calling (moſt Reuerend Father) that God hath promoted your Grace vnto, by the vn-erring hand of his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Deputie, to be their Agent, <hi>in cauſis maioribus,</hi> to the Churches of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, may iuſtly challenge the labours of as many as handle the pen with diſcretion in our daies; but mine (if J be ought) af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:8954:3"/>a more eſpeciall manner: whom, the continuance of your fauour, for no fewe yeares, ſhining vpon my poore ſtudies, hath made wholly pledged to your ſeruice; and ſome employments alſo vouchſafed from your Grace, haue kept from being altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther idle. So that if my meanneſſe ſhould euer bee exalted to bring forth any thing worthy publication (which your Grace ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther construeth ouer-fauourably of this Pamphlet, than it any way deſerueth) J haue long ſince conſecrated it to the honor of your Grace, as one that hath both coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced alwaies mine endeauours, and alſo directed, after a ſort, my courſes. Howbeit, this ſmall worke, ſuch as it is J now preſent vnto your Grace, not ſo much in lieu of receiued kindneſſe (which you haue multiplied vpon me and mine, euen when your name hath beene concealed) as inuoking patronage against the oppug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.
<pb facs="tcp:8954:3"/>For, <hi>lata porta,</hi> but <hi>aduerſarij multi,</hi> as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid to his; <hi>1. Cor. 16.9.</hi> and <hi>As concerning this way, wee knowe nothing, but that it is euery where ſpoken againſt;</hi> as they ſaid to S. <hi>Paul, Act. 28.22.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>J ſpeake the truth in Christ (moſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend Father) I lie not, the holy Ghost alſo bearing witneſſe with my conſcience; that J grieue vnſpeakeably, night and day, whitherſoeuer J chaunce to looke, at the malice of Satan (how transfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ſoeuer) and the diſaster of our times. And as our Sauiour ſometimes, in the dayes of his fleſh, wept in compaſsion o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <hi>the great Citie,</hi> diuining the ruines of it: ſo mine eyes guſh out with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to ſee there is no religion amongst menne for the most part, but that which is tainted with a ſpice of facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8954:4"/>
            <p> But to let-go complaints, and to leaue that to him which will purge his floore in a due time, as one that hath his fan already in his hand, and lets the yellow weedes to ſhoote vp but in a policie, to exerciſe our patience, and to magnifie his wiſedome in the latter end: as for the Booke, my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort is, that whom the reuerence of your Graces mildneſse and temper, most befit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the aduancement of his <hi>chaire,</hi> ſhall not repreſse for ſhame; him the edge of your iudgement, long ſince tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and renowmed for the most accurate peruſall of theſe cauſes and controuerſies, aboue all the Church-men of our Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhall daunt perforce.</p>
            <p>And with that very hope J end for this time; humbly recommending the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperities of your Grace, and the good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of the Church Christian, to the Lord Christ: that vnder your auſpicious and
<pb facs="tcp:8954:4"/>happie gouernement (which God of his mercy graunt may be moſt moſt long) our Nazarites may bee whiter than the ſnow, &amp; our Priests purer than the Sap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phires.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Graces moſt humble Chaplaine and Seruant,SAMVEL COLLINS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:8954:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:8954:5"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at <hi>Paules</hi>-Croſſe.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1. TIMOTH. 6.3.4.5.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>If any man teach otherwiſe, and conſenteth not to the wholeſom words of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and to the doctrine which is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording vnto godlineſſe, hee is puft vp, and knoweth nothing, but languiſheth about queſtions, and ſtrife of words, whereof commeth enuy, ſtrife, raylings, euill ſurmiſes, froward diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of men of corrupt mindes, and deſtitute of the truth, which thinke that gaine is godlineſſe: from ſuch ſeparate thy ſelfe.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.17. thus wee reade, that vpon a day there came, out of the hoaſt of the Philiſtines, three garriſons of Champions, all minded to deſtroie; but, each turning ſeuerall waies, one to <hi>Ophrah,</hi> another to <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoron,</hi> and a third to <hi>Zeboim.</hi> This was a pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Churches condition, not only bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily then waſted, and afflicted for the time, but
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:8954:6"/>ſpiritually aſſaulted to the ends of the world: whome a trebble ſquadron of conſpiring eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies all bent to murther and deſtroy, yet all attempting ſundrie means to miſchief, do mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt continually; the heretique by his poiſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous and corrupt doctrines, the euill liuer by his ſcandalous and wicked examples, the ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matique by his turbulent and vnchriſtian ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</p>
               <p>And, againſt theſe, the <hi>Ionathans</hi> of God with their Captain <hi>Saul,</hi> higher by the head than all the children of Iſrael, that is the king and his Clergie, muſt alwaies haue their weapons in readineſſe to ſuppreſs their furies. We, the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt of ten thouſand, doe it as wee may to the vtmoſt of our power, and haue done it often heretofore in diuers places, encountring them and coping with them, as the occaſion guided vs, either iointly all at once, or diuidedly by themſelues.</p>
               <p>This day wee will ſingle out the Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick from his fellowes, as in a ſtage of renown, the greateſt diſturber (if my mind do not miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue mee) that our Church hath complained vnder, theſe many yeares. And yet we wil pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue him nor chaſe him no further, than S. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf ſhall giue vs leaue to do, nay ayme and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:8954:6"/>ſcope how to doe, in the Text now propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
               <p>The parts whereof are in effect theſe ſixe; pleaſe you to peruſe them with mee. The firſt is, <hi>The indifferency of the parties offending,</hi> in theſe words, <hi>If any man,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; <hi>Jf any,</hi> bee hee who he wil be, high or lowe, rich or poor, great or ſmall, learned or lay, famous or of no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, <hi>If any.</hi> The ſecond is <hi>the Quality of the fact; conſenteth not,</hi> agreeth not, accordeth not, I had almoſt ſaide ſubſcribeth not. The third is <hi>the degree of the fault; teach otherwiſe:</hi> not only think, but teach, publiſh his fancies, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime his conceits, drawe Diſciples after him, make a Sect, and blowe a trumpet to ſedition with <hi>Siba</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Bichri, Euerie man to his Tents, O Jſrael,</hi> the 2. of <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.1. The fourth is <hi>the rule of tryall</hi> for this matter, <hi>the ſquare of truth</hi> to diſcerne and iudge by: It ſelfe two-folde; eyther <hi>the wholeſome wordes of</hi> CHRIST <hi>and of godlineſse,</hi> or <hi>euerie doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine according thereto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So I ſay, not only the written word of God, but euery doctrine that is not diſſenting or ſwaruing there-from; not onely that which is expreſſed, but that which is inferred, and by interpoſition of lawfull authoritie deducted,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:8954:7"/>not onely that which is originally good, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen that which is conſequentially ſound, <hi>the wholeſom words and the doctrine according;</hi> that is the fourth part as I ſaid. The fift is the <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi> and this is ſomewhat intricate: I pray you mark it the better, to ſaue my labour. Firſt, <hi>priuatiue, he knoweth nothing,</hi> he is an Idiot, an <hi>ignaro,</hi> a very childe inwardly, whatſoeuer he pretend &amp; vaunt for outwardly. Secondly, <hi>poſitiue,</hi> &amp; that either <hi>Cauſal</hi> in the firſt place &amp; <hi>radicall, he is puft vp:</hi> for, <hi>Radix omnis peccati ſuperbia,</hi> Pride is the root of euery ſinne, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially of this ſinne, Schiſme and ſeparation in the Church. Secondly, <hi>formall,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>languiſheth about queſtions:</hi> He languiſheth indeede, and ſpendeth his ſtrength in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tention &amp; brabble. <hi>Hippocrates</hi> himſelf could ſay no more to diſco<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer the nature of the diſeaſe. It is a head pain, that I ſay not a heady; and <hi>Caput dolet, caput dolet,</hi> as the childe complayned, 2. <hi>King.</hi> 4.19. But the fathers anſwer is very wiſe and good, <hi>Carry him to his mother,</hi> Let the Church cenſure him and correct him: That, if any thing, may chaunce to heale him. Thirdly, <hi>Euentuall</hi> or <hi>effectiue, of which commeth enuie, ſtrife, raylings, euill ſurmiſes:</hi> you may ſay they are Legion, they are ſo manie, or heere comes
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:8954:7"/>a company, they are ſo thick; as <hi>Leab</hi> ſaide at the birth of <hi>Gad, Gen.</hi> 30.11. And yet ye haue not al, but laſt of all diſputations, diſputations, I ſay, or at leaſt offers &amp; challenges to diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: let the times interpret me. Fourthly, <hi>qualitatiue,</hi> from the diſpoſitions of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons themſelues, and that threefolde; In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde of their iudgement, in regarde of their affection, and in regard of their practice. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of their iudgement, <hi>deſtitute of the truth,</hi> and therfore blinde. In regard of their affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>corruptly minded,</hi> partially minded, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore crooked; pretending one thing, intending and ayming at another. Thirdly, and laſtly in regarde of their practice, <hi>thinking gaine to bee godlineſſe,</hi> or placing their godlineſſe in gaine, as the Prophet DAVID ſayth of them in the Pſalm, <hi>Therfore doe the people fal vnto them, and therout ſuck they no ſmall aduantage.</hi> This was the fift mayn part, the <hi>Cenſure.</hi> The ſixt and laſt ſtill remaineth: which you may call the <hi>Caution</hi> or the <hi>Jnhibition; From ſuch ſeparate thy ſelfe.</hi> So haue you, to make ſhort, the <hi>indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferency of the parties,</hi> the <hi>qualitie of the facte,</hi> the <hi>degree of the faulte,</hi> the <hi>rule of tryall or</hi> the <hi>ſquare of truth,</hi> the <hi>Cenſure</hi> and the <hi>Inhibition:</hi> For I omit the ſeuerall branches of amplifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:8954:8"/>til I com to the handling. And of al theſe, or of ſom of theſe, as God ſhal giue vtterance, you patience, and the time allowance.</p>
               <p>I haue propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded the parts, I muſt confeſſe, ſomwhat otherwiſe than they ly in the Text (as preferring order of matter before order of wordes in the Apoſtles writings); and yet I ſee I muſt handle them ſomwhat otherwiſe than <hi>I</hi> propounded them: but all ſhall be directed to the eaſier apprehenſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of you that are the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors, &amp; no force offered to holy ſcripture.</p>
               <p>To begin therfore firſt with <hi>the quality of the fact,</hi> in thoſe words, <hi>If any conſent not;</hi> the Pela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gian as ſoone as he heares of this <hi>Conſent,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentlie dreams a dream of his dearling <hi>Freewil,</hi> as if all ſheaues bowed to hir ſheaue, and ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines we may do this by the power of Nature, I mean yield aſſent to the heauenly reuelation.</p>
               <p>But if <hi>the naturall man perceiue not the things of God,</hi> 1. Cor. 2.14. much leſſe can hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to them out of his powers naturall, after once hee perceiues them. For, conſenting is the harder, perceiuing is the eaſier of the two. As for example, I can make a man that hath but an ordinarie capacitie, by my pithie declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to perceiue what wee meane by the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the Trinitie, folded vp in reuerend ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcuritie,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:8954:8"/>by the incarnation of Chriſt that ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes vp the ſenſe both of men and Angells: but I cannot make him aſſent to it nor agree to it; <hi>digitus Dei hic eſt,</hi> this point ſurpaſſeth our skill, &amp; it is Gods finger alone that can import a conſent, though wee can imprint a conceit: he bowes the neck of the inner man, and puts our feete into wiſdomes fetters, our hands into her links and chaines, mollifies and intenerates that ſame <hi>neruum ferreum</hi> (as <hi>Manaſses</hi> calls it) the iron ſynew of our vnbeliefe. <hi>Nemo pugna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit in valle Terebinthi</hi> (ſayth S.
<note place="margin">Serm. de Temp.</note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> moſt ſweetly) <hi>donec</hi> Dauid <hi>veniret ad praelium,</hi> ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the hiſtorie of <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Goliah;</hi> that is, no man fought in the valleie of Turpentine trees, till <hi>Dauid</hi> came and vndertook the chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge. So, no man is of force in this dale of mortalitie to act anie point of ghoſtly chiual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, till the ſpirit of Chriſt which is the truer <hi>Dauid</hi> ſhall come vpon him, and the power of the moſt high ſhall ouerſhadow him: of Chriſt I ſay, who is therfore called, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Hebrues.</hi> 12.2. The beginner and the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, the founder and the finiſher, the <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega</hi> of our faith. For, as he beginnes it <hi>in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecto,</hi> ſo he ends it <hi>in cauſa:</hi> as he did what wee might beleeue, ſo hee helpes vs to beleeue
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:8954:9"/>what he hath done for vs, ſhining in the darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe (if at leaſt any will comprehend him) and illightning euerie man that commeth into this world. We reade how <hi>Hiram</hi> was famous for his working and caruing in braſſe. 1. <hi>King.</hi> 7.14. But the truer praiſe hereof (if you mark it wel) belongs to him, who only writes his Laws in our hearts, and giues vs heart for heart, <hi>Cor carneumpro lapideo,</hi> a heart of fleſh for a heart of ſtone, ſupple and gentle for rough and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractable, and renewes a right ſpirit within vs in the middeſt of our bowelles. <hi>Anatomize</hi> if you pleaſe with me the parts of <hi>Christian</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: what are they? I ſuppoſe theſe; Thought, Faith, Wil, Deed, Perſeuerance, Martyrdom. What more eaſie then to thinke? yet wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſo much as thinke a good thought of our ſelues, as of our ſelues, ſaith the Apoſtle. What, next thinking, more eaſie then beleeuing? yet ye are ſaued by faith: which faith is not of your ſelues, it is the gift of God. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2.8. What then like willing and affecting? yet it is he that worketh in vs both to will and to doe, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his good pleaſure. But at leaſt we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and accompliſh his onſets after hee hath once begunne them in vs: No, but he which hath begunue the good work in you will fulfill
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:8954:9"/>it vnto the end. Much leſſe then can we ſuffer but by his ſupportance, if we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not do without his aſſiſtance: yea verily; for ſo we read, to you it is giuen, (marke the word <hi>giuen</hi>) not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to belieue in him, but to ſuffer for him. Thus you ſee, nothing ſo eaſie that he diſdai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth for vs; nothing againe ſo hard, but he ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecteth it by vs. As to the one kinde wee are more than weak and feeble, without him: ſo of the other kind we are more than Conquerors, through him. For, as Chriſt ſayth by vs, <hi>With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out me you can do nothing:</hi> ſo we ſay by him, that <hi>in Chriſt which enableth vs, we can do all things.</hi> And, in one word, my deare brethren, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer progreſſe we make, whatſoeuer ſtep wee ſet forward vpon this <hi>Jacobs</hi> ladder, the way of grace and vertue which conducteth our ſoules to bliſſe; ſtil <hi>Dominus ſuper ſcalam</hi> (as S.
<note place="margin">Serm. de Temp.</note> 
                  <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> hath obſerued out of <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.13.) ſtill the Lord is aboue the Ladder, ſtill Chriſt the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell is conſpicuous at the toppe.</p>
               <p>And yet we read, ſaies the Pelagian, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 1.19 <hi>Jf you conſent &amp; obey, you ſhall eat the good things of the earth:</hi> but do we not reade againe; <hi>Jt is not of the willer, nor yet of the runner, but of God that ſheweth mercy.</hi> And yet we read, ſaies the Pelagian, <hi>I haue inclined my hart to keep thy righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teous
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:8954:10"/>iudgements:</hi> but doe we not read againe, in the ſame Pſalme; <hi>O Lord doe thou incline my heart vnto thy testimonies, &amp; not to couetouſnes.</hi> And yet we read, ſaies the Pelagian, <hi>My ſon, keepe thy heart with all diligence;</hi> as if hee were his hearts keeper: but doe we not read again, <hi>The peace of God, which paſseth al vnderſtanding, keep your hearts &amp; mindes in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and yet we read ſaies the Pelag. <hi>Make you ſtrait ſteps vnto your feet, leaſt that which is hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting be turned out of the waie.</hi> Heb. 12.13: but do we not read again, ſay I, <hi>Order (O Lord) my goings in thy paths, that my footſteps ſlide not;</hi> and <hi>Take thou from me the way of lying, but leade mee in the way euerlaſting.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How then is it, my dear brethren? for, I may ſeem to haue led you into a maze of wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>drings: or how may theſe contradictions ſo great in ſhew, be knit vp in any ſubſtantial accordance? yes doubtleſs, very wel: neither delighteth in the others ouerthrow, but both eſpouſe frend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in the kiſs of peace. Free-wil eats not vp grace, as <hi>Pharaohs</hi> leane kine eat vp the fat, nor grace deuours not Free-will (<hi>Adolet non abolet natura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gratia,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Proſper</hi>) as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſerpents deuoured the Inchanters: but the ſword of the Lord and the ſword of <hi>Gedeon,</hi> Gods finger and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:8954:10"/>humane indeuor, may both ſtand togither ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wel. And in one word, to finiſh this, becauſe the time ſpendeth ſo faſt; As in the caſe of the perſon of our glorious Sauiour, we ſearch the Scriptures to ſee what he was, and to redeeme him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſlanderous deprauation of toongs, ſome denying him to be God, ſome denying him to be man; we (I ſay) ſearch the Scriptures about this point, go into the ſanctuarie, &amp; fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him wearie ſitting at a Well, finding him hungrie, finding him thirſty, ſleeping, bleeding mourning, dying, and ſuch like, we conclude a man; but conſidering him on the other ſide, trampling the waters, quieting the winds, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the tempeſts, rebuking fevers, taming the diuels, whipping out the Simoniacall bargai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Temple, we infer a God: So in this doubtfull diuerſitie, where ſome denie grace, ſom aboliſh Nature and Free-vvill, we turn the book, the book of deciſion for the weightie cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and controuerſies of God; and if propen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion on the one ſide make for liberty, grace on the other ſide appears in victorie, neither defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing nor demoliſhing the other, like <hi>Dagon,</hi> and the Arke; but each countenancing and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhing, like the 2. Cherubins that behelde one thing, and yet looked both ſundrie waies.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:8954:11"/>
               <p> For, if anie man <hi>conſent not,</hi> as you haue it in the Text, <hi>If hee conſent not,</hi> implyes not a conſenting power in vs. No, though he had ſayd, ſee that you conſent, looke that you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; yet, that proues no ability of doing ſo: neither ſuppoſition, nor impoſition, neither <hi>ſi,</hi> nor <hi>ſic</hi> can euicte anie ſuch concluſion at our hands: but, <hi>Lex imperat, fides impetrat;</hi> the Law indeed was giuen by <hi>Moſes</hi> to the end that it ſhould driue vs to the grace that comes by Chriſt: and commandement may extend far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than ſtrength. As when we read <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. <hi>Ver.</hi> 4. <hi>Tupraecepisti,</hi> thou haſt charged that we ſhould diligently keepe thy commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, he adds not, nor collects not, There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I can, or, therfore I will, as the Pelagian would do in all the haſte; but, <hi>O that my waies were made ſo direct that I might keep thy ſtatutes.</hi> The <hi>Imperatiue</hi> begets an <hi>Optatiue,</hi> not a <hi>Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial</hi> with <hi>him:</hi> for, <hi>Da Domine quod iubes, &amp; iube quod vis,</hi> Lord help me but to performe, and then I care not what thou require. And ſo much might ſuffice to haue ſpoken, of <hi>Conſent;</hi> but that the age, which we are falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into, craues a word more by way of this diſcourſe at my hands. I will obey the times, and yet not neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the time.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:8954:11"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Conſent,</hi> is of three ſorts, euen as it may be performed by three diſtinct Organs; the heart, the mouth, the hand. The <hi>Conſent</hi> of the heart is called <hi>Faith,</hi> of the mouth is tearmed <hi>Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> of the hand is <hi>Subſcription.</hi> For, ſo ſaith S. <hi>Paul;</hi> not content with one without the other, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.10. <hi>With the heart we belieue to righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,</hi> that is but one ſtep: and, <hi>with the mouth we confeſſe to ſaluation,</hi> that is another ſtep: and he might adde a third, yea hee addes it heer in effect (or at leaſt, for ſo many as ſhall be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and called vpon) <hi>with the hand we ſubſcribe,</hi> to maintain good order and keep all from run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning into endleſſe confuſion. Or, if you will haue one ſpeake plainer for this third kinde of <hi>Conſent,</hi> than S. <hi>Paul</hi> heere doth; take but the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> to you, who in his 44. &amp; 5, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telling of our times, the times of the new teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, makes <hi>ſubſcription of the hand,</hi> in direct tearms, one a principal mark of our honorable Chriſtendome; <hi>They ſhall ſubſcribe</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>with their hand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But alas! what ſhould I ſay more in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, if neither the <hi>Parallel of Scripture,</hi> nor <hi>the precedent of ſtorie,</hi> nor <hi>the manifest neceſsitie of the thing it ſelf,</hi> nor your owne <hi>practice of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon life</hi> can perſwade you? <hi>J</hi> wil briefly touch them all.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:8954:12"/>
               <p> Firſt, the <hi>Parallel of Scripture:</hi> The Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates generally brought their people to make a couenant with Allmightie GOD, that they woulde continue in his ſeruice, and in obedience to his lavves as concerning Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Joſua,</hi> 24.25. I vvill make ſhort. The place was <hi>Shechem;</hi> the Act was, writing the peoples words of <hi>Conſent,</hi> and vvriting them in the book of the lavv of God; the ceremonie vvas a ſtone rolled vnder an Oke that vvas in the Sanctuarie: vvhich ſtone vvas to be a vvit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their promiſed conformitie.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Joſiah,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 23.3. He renevv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the like couenant again between God and the people, and eſtabliſhed vniformitie of vvorſhip by a vovv. And though there be no mention, in that place, of vvriting, and taking names as in the former; yet either vve muſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it ſo by conference of places (though for breuitie ſake it be omitted in the one) or at leaſt it hath the ſame force: &amp; I doubt not but as <hi>Job</hi> ſaies of his words, <hi>O that my words were written in a book;</hi> ſo, none there profeſſed but could vvell be content to haue it regiſtred, &amp; the honour of that daies Act to remaine vvith <hi>Zebulun</hi> the handler of the pen, <hi>Judges,</hi> 5, 14.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:8954:12"/>as well as with <hi>Napthali,</hi> the delicate Hinde, ſmooth of language, and giuing goodly words. <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.21.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, and laſtly <hi>Nehemiah</hi> in his 9. and 38. where, in fewe words you haue this, a ſure <hi>Couenant</hi> as <hi>Ioſiah</hi> made; and the writing of it, as in <hi>Joſuah</hi> we ſawe; and yet, beſide that, the ſeale put to it: which was more then in anie of the former: So much briefly for <hi>Parallel of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture.</hi> As for the <hi>precedent of ſtorie,</hi> infinite might be alleaged: but <hi>J</hi> wil inſiſt in only one, ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous as it cannot be denied, and ſo pregnant as it may by no meanes be deſpiſed. <hi>Arius</hi> (<hi>J</hi> ſpeake no more than almoſt all of you know) who driuing ambitiouſly at a Biſhopwrick,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Theod. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſt. hiſt. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 2</note> was preuented therein by <hi>Alexander</hi> his Competi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, the worthier man, though perhaps not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed his equall for heate of zeale, miſſing his ſuit, purſued his ſpite by broaching an here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie as derogatorie to the head, as theſe of our daies are to the bodie (<hi>J</hi> meane to Chriſt, as theſe bee to his Church) that hee might ſeem ſomebody, for all the repulſe, and dravve a world of malcontents after him. The Councel of <hi>Nice</hi> gathered for that purpoſe by the holie Ghoſt, to quenche the fire that had kindled ſo farre, and yet was like to ſpreade a great
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:8954:13"/>deale farther, ſent for this <hi>Arius,</hi> conferred with him, debated the cauſe, draue him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, &amp; demanded <hi>Subſcription</hi> of him: which in the end he denied not. So antient is the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of requiring <hi>ſubſcription</hi> at the hands of Church-men, to preuent faction once a-foot. Now, if <hi>Arius</hi> ſubſcribed but haltingly, and diſſemblingly, retaining the poiſon of his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion at heart, which he couered ſo cunningly with the ſugar of tearmes, as many doe now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies (with whom it is, not as with <hi>Pilate, quod ſcripſi, ſcripſi,</hi> what <hi>J</hi> haue written, <hi>J</hi> haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; but, the Chapman inuerted, of whome <hi>Salonion</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>It is good, it is good,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward falls to diſpraiſe it againe) <hi>J</hi> ſay, if this be ſo, yet that detracts not from <hi>ſubſcription,</hi> as if leſſe lawfull and laudable for that cauſe; but ſhewes in truth, that ſome ſtronger cordes would be prouided, if it were poſſible, to ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per theſe colts (that ſnuff the winde, as <hi>Ieremie</hi> ſaith, and whiske it in the wilderneſſe of their owne boundleſſe and tranſported fancie) from ſtraying and breaking foorth of the limites a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Yea verely, let <hi>Shimei</hi> be confined to the Riuer <hi>Kidron</hi> for gadding, 1. <hi>King.</hi> 2.42. and make Renegates conſtant euen againſt their will.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:8954:13"/>
               <p> The third head was from <hi>the manifeſt neceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the thing it ſelfe:</hi> wherein, <hi>J</hi> ſhall need to ſay the leſſe, becauſe your owne ſenſes may be your owne Iudges, and experience yieldeth her plentifull teſtimonie. <hi>The heart of man</hi> (ſaith the Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi>) <hi>is like a great ſea,</hi> huge, and bottomleſſe; <hi>who can fadome it?</hi> and <hi>Salomon, This one thing yet haue J found, that GOD hath made man righteous, but bee hath begotten to himſelfe manie inuentions:</hi> Manie, manie, whereof there is no number; and yet more would, were there no reſtraint. Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, my deare Brethren, if Order bee a thing ſo much to bee deſired (<hi>Let all things bee done comelie and in good order.</hi> 1. Corinthians, 14.40.) <hi>And if God be the God, not of confuſion, but of peace, &amp; ſo J teach in al the Churches</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) and if Order bee ranked with Faith in another place, for the excellency of it (as <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> 2.5, <hi>J delight to ſee your Order, and your ſtabliſhed Faith</hi>) and, if the Church bee tearmed <hi>terrible like an Armie with banners,</hi> only becauſe of the goodly arraie that ſhe mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth in; then thinke, what you muſt needes think of ſubſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vnleſs you wil needs think amiſs: without which, we ſhould haue (I trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſpeak it) ſo many pariſhes, ſo many part-takings,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:8954:14"/>ſo manie companies, ſo manie rents in Chriſts coate, ſo manie congregations, ſo manie diſtractions, ſo manie Churches, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie ſects; yea, more than ſo, <hi>quot capita, tot ſchiſmata,</hi> as S. <hi>Jerom</hi> ſaith; ſo manie men, ſo manie mindes: and conſequently, ſo many ſchiſmes, growing, and budding out of them; Gods inheritance being like <hi>Jeremies</hi> bird, a <hi>bird of diuers colours.</hi> Ier. 12.9. and faction mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplying without all meaſure, like <hi>Anacreons</hi> fonde loues, ſome perfect, ſome pipient, ſome hatcht, ſome half hatcht, ſome peering out of the egge, ſome riper in the chick; while others had the ſtrength to flie nimbly awaie. <hi>Seneca</hi> reports, that the wiſe Senators of antient <hi>Rome</hi> were content for a time to let the ſlaues goe diſtinguiſhed from the free-borne in apparell; the wearing of the cappe making the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene them and the Citizen: till at laſt they eſpyed, there vvas this inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in it, that the ſlaues might happilie fall to numbring of their ovvne ſide, and ſo to preſume vppon their ovvne ſtrength, till in the end it ſhould breake out into open rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion. Let this bee but practiced heere a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle amongſt vs, in the Church of GOD, euery congregation doing as they liſt, and aſſuming
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:8954:14"/>to themſelues what faſhion they liſt, till it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to bee conſidered, who haue the moſt of their ſide; and we ſhall not neede to be threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Jſmaels</hi> fiſt, though the time was when we were threatned it, as you know; their bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, no doubt, ſpringing out of ſome ſuch obſeruacion: vvee ſhould haue felt it, <hi>J</hi> warrant you, walking about our eares euen by this time.</p>
               <p>The fourth, and the laſt, is your owne <hi>prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice in common life.</hi> I confeſs, I am loth to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to ſuch ſpecialties, that <hi>J</hi> may not ſay to ſuch triuialties: but you muſt be conuicted by your owne proceedings; who, for ſubſtantiall aſſurance, vſe the Scriuener, &amp; the Indenture, almoſt to euerie thing. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſaith Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> of olde, that is, you bind vs in, with writings, ſtronger than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie iron chaines. So as S. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to <hi>Philemon,</hi> but about a matter of debt, betweene him and <hi>Oneſimus</hi> his runne. awaie ſeruant, was faine to deſcend to your tearms, and to your conditions, though he were an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle; and, after promiſe of repayment made, thus to ſaie, <hi>Ego ſubſcripſimanu mea,</hi> I haue ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed it with mine own hand, feare not: in the Epiſtle to <hi>Philem. Ver.</hi> 19.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:8954:15"/>
               <p> Yea, the Naule was vſed in former times, by Gods owne appointment, to bore-through the eare of him, that woulde not depart from his firſt ſeruice: <hi>Deut.</hi> 15.17. And do you think much, if they be put to the pen, to keep them from backe ſliding, and from Apoſtaſie, that ſerue indeed, and ſerue not at the Tabernacle (which was but the patterne &amp; ſhadow of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly things. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.5) but are the immediate Miniſters of the truth of the liuing God?</p>
               <p>But, <hi>Subſcription</hi> they will ſay, they all allow of, &amp; no bodie takes exception againſt the vſe of the thing; they refuſe to ſubſcribe to ſuch, and ſuch Articles. What Articles I praie you? Som dangerous ones, I warrant you, that our Church obtrudeth, that ſterne ſtep-mother, and much of kinne to thoſe that <hi>Jobs</hi> Wife commenced to him; <hi>Blaspheame GOD and dye.</hi> It were tedious to goe ouer all that is controuerted, and which hath beene iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied vppon our ſide, ouer and ouer againe, as cleare as it were written with the brighteſt Sunne-beam vpon a wall of glaſſe as <hi>Lactan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> ſpeaketh. And, if ſo much inke, as hath been already ſpent in the cauſes, cannot ceaſe the Ring-worme of creeping contention; how then maie <hi>J</hi> thinke, that my tongue,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:8954:15"/>will be ſo ſoueraigne and ſo medicinable (lick it neuer ſo cunningly nor ſo cleanly) as to cure the <hi>Lazar</hi> of ſuch an inueterate ſore? Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone muſt be inuoked, and his good ſpirit im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plored, that ſhall ſtaunch the wound, and drie vp the iſſue of feſtered bloud, that hath vexed our <hi>Syrophaeniſſian</hi> woman, the Church of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> in theſe Northerne parts of the world, now more than theſe 8 yeares.</p>
               <p>Vnleſſe you looke I ſhould defend our Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and <hi>Hierarchies;</hi> which they ſay are <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christian,</hi> we knowe to be <hi>Apostolique:</hi> our ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite and veſtments; which, they thinke, are ſo farre off from the Camels skinne, that they are made of the Dragons taile: the imperfections of our prayer-book; which they haue made to ſtinke in the noſtrils of men, as much as euer it ſmelt ſweet in the noſtrils of God: our praying for all men; which, they ſay, is againſt particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar election: for all that trauaile by Land, or by water; which, they ſay, is for Theeues and Pirats: againſt lightning and tempeſts; which, they ſay, is againſt ſparrow-blaſting, vnleſſe it be at a certaine time of the yeare onely: that our Fathers ſins ſit not heauie vpon our ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; which, they ſay, is to acknowledge Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie: that we be hurt by no perſecutions; as
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:8954:16"/>much in effect, as that we may lead a quiet and a peaceable life; the very words of S. <hi>Paul.</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2: Our entreating Chriſt by his agony, &amp; bloudie paſſion; which they call coniuring: our Miniſteriall abſolution; which to them ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uors of a Popes pardon: and laſtly, our Croſſe in holy Baptiſme, ſo ſcandalous, that ſame <hi>Lig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num iuxta aquas,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Serm. de Temp.</note> as S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſweetly calls it, the Tree of the Croſſe that is planted by the waters of Baptiſme; which theſe good men, for want of other matter, call idolatry.</p>
               <p>I paſſe by many things: theſe that I haue me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, are too too vnſauorie; and I am loath to giue you a ſurfet of diſtaſte. If wiſe men be not deceiued, they are more offended with our ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice-booke, for that which it hath not, than for that which it hath.</p>
               <p>As for theſe that I haue mentioned, what ſhould I ſay? there are ſome things ſo cleare, as they refuſe triall; ſome ſlaunders ſo lewde and ſo baſe, as they abhorre purgation. Your good apprehenſion muſt be our beſt perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; your capacitie our Oratorie.</p>
               <p>So much for the firſt point, <hi>The quality of the fact; If he conſent not.</hi> The 2. followeth, which is, <hi>the degree of the fault; If he teach otherwiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I muſt be ſhort in that behind is; this 1. hath deuoured ſo much good time already.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:8954:16"/>
               <p>ALl faults are not of one and the ſame de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree: ſome are ſmaller, ſom greater, ſom lighter, ſome more haynous. There is a mote and a beame, there is ſtubble and Lead, there is iudgement, or councel, or hel fire pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable. <hi>If hee conſent not,</hi> that is <hi>Ianua mortis,</hi> to ſpeake with <hi>Origen;</hi> but, <hi>If he teach o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe,</hi> that is <hi>limen inferni.</hi> Our Sauiour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe diſtinguiſheth theſe ſo: <hi>Math.</hi> 5.19. <hi>Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ſhall breake one of theſe leaſt commandements</hi> (and yet they count ſome ſo little &amp; ſo petite, as they are not worth the keeping; the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies being no better with theſe men, than a Cupbord of glaſſes, that they may daſh at their pleaſure, forſooth): but, as I was ſaying, Our Sauiour makes a difference betweene <hi>whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer breakes,</hi> and <hi>breaking teacheth ſo,</hi> one euen of the leaſt commaundements: or rather hee couples them, and ioynes them together; to ſhew they ſeldome go aſunder. Which is the cauſe, that <hi>S. Paul</hi> alſo reckons them for one here in this place, <hi>If hee conſent not,</hi> and, <hi>If hee teach otherwiſe.</hi> For, <hi>ſerpit vt Cancer,</hi> as the ſame Apoſtle ſaide of olde, ſuch Doctrine ſtill creepes like a Gangrene, frets, proceedes, ſtayes not; it hath a power infecting like the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:8954:17"/>eye of a Baſiliske: and if <hi>Archytas</hi> take no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in vicuing heauen, with all the heauenly beauties thereof, vnleſſe he may haue one to tell it to againe, the Diuell (ſaith <hi>S. Cyprian</hi>) ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his condemnation, and ſo doe his agents, with this, if they can draw as many after them, as poſsibly may be, into the ſame pit of error.</p>
               <p>It is moſt true, <hi>Hoc fonte deriuata clades,</hi> and I may well add the reſt, <hi>in patriam populum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fluxit:</hi> this is the originall of all our woe, the deſperate licentiouſneſſe of the Teacher. As when a well-ſpring is poyſoned, the trauailer muſt needes die for it, that drinks thereof, and all the beaſts of the Forreſt, and all the birds a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the branches, and the wilde Aſſes that quench their thirſt there; as the Pſalmiſt ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth: ſo fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the mouth of the Teacher ſpreads this venome into the veines of the body, till it leaue no place voide of a mortall contagion. But <hi>execrabilis ille qui minxit in torrentem,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the olde ſaying; accurſed be hee that hath thus poiſoned our Current. If <hi>Ahab</hi> muſt be deceiued, there is no fitter meanes to deceiue him by, than for <hi>ſpiritus mendacij,</hi> a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpirit, to get into the mouth of one of his Prophets, and from that Pulpit to preach as it pleaſeth him 1. <hi>Kings</hi> 22.22. Al the aberrations
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:8954:17"/>and corruptions of the people, both <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Iuda,</hi> are generally fathered throughout the Bible, vpon the tongues of the Prophets, that taught partially: and God himſelfe acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth, that their ſowre grape ſet the peoples teeth on edge; the Serpent gaue it them, and they gaue it the people. For, whereas they ſhould haue beene like an Oracle reſponſall, without any <hi>Philippizing,</hi> to the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, their lippes preſeruing knowledge with indifferencie, and the Lawe beeing to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired and rendred at their mouth; they on the contrary preacht: what? <hi>Viſionem cordis, &amp; non ex ore Domini,</hi> a viſion of their owne heart, and not out of the mouth of the Lord: which, to interpret by our times, were a dreame of their owne braine, begotten of choler and a hungry ſtomach, fore-telling the downefall of the Prelates and the Cleargie, with an imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie ſcambling after the reuenews of Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks.</p>
               <p>And if it pleaſe you but to heare a little what may be ſaide in this behalfe for condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Teachers, acquitting and releaſing the poore ignorant people; you (may they ſay, turning to their Teachers) taught vs to aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the congregation, where prayers were but
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:8954:18"/>read out of a booke: you to fling out of the Church in a fume, where any thing ſounded but canonicall Scripture, though neuer ſo wholſom elſe to be hearkned to you to damn Homilies to the pit of hell, which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained the kernell of ſaluation more liuely, than all your vocall Sermons could euer amount to: you to meaſure Baptiſme by the perſon that admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred it, as if no Preacher were no ſufficient baptizer; a thing ſo contrarie to all the rules of Diuinitie, that the principall Apoſtle ſayes of himſelf, <hi>He was ſent to the one &amp; not to the other:</hi> you to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et the Baptiſme of our new born babes, like a thing indifferent at ſix and ſeauens; as if the righteouſneſſe of the Parents made them perfect before God, that were borne in ſin and in damnation, and the ſauing Sacrament were now but a complement: You to bite the lip, and hang the head, at Supremacie of princes, in each kinde of cauſes, mentioned in prayers; as if that were but flatterie, beeing caſt vpon kings, and the truer right thereof in Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call menages belonged to the Presbiters. You to flie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Surplice &amp; the Cap, as fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſhe Beare robbed of her whelps in the wilderneſſe, whereas <hi>that defileth not that goeth into a man,</hi> much leſſe that which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth vpon him, ſaith our Sauior, &amp;
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.14</note> there is nothing vnclean, but to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:8954:18"/>him that thinketh ſo. And how ſhal we reckon vp al your other myſteries, that you were wont to incomber vs with? You, to put great holines, in not bending at Communion; high religion, in refraining from ſolemne thankſgiuing after child-birth: main diſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in withholding our children from the moſt godly <hi>confirmation;</hi> deep iudgement in abhorring the ring as a ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill pledge at Mariage. This may the people ſay of their Teachers, &amp; this muſt their excuſe be, in the laſt day, when they ſhal be charged to haue wakened the ſpouſe of Chriſt, &amp; troubled her reſt afore ſhe would. <hi>Oues aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iſtae quid me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruerunt?</hi> as for theſe poore ſheep, that haue bin thus beguiled, what alas haue they deſerued?</p>
               <p>Howbeit, heere I cannot excuſe the people altogether, of this our Land, ſo as fain I would, but that a great part of the fault ſtill reſteth on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; who, though at firſt they were angled with the enticing words of their new Prophets, yet afterward ſo plaid vpon the hook, as in the end they could not be beaten fro it &amp; the prophets now, if they would pleaſe them, might caſt no other bait before the but that. So as a man may ſay, that if at firſt they were credited becauſe they ſpoke it, now they were to ſpeake it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they wold be credited: a very ball of factio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:8954:19"/>being thus toſſed in a manner, to and fro, what betweene the politique drifts of the Teacher, at his firſt entrance; and the licorouſneſſe of the Auditors, now, not onely eaſie to be taken, but iealous, if the taker applied any meanes, but thoſe wherewith they were firſt taken. And yet euen this againe is no more, than the Church of the Iſraelites ſaw in olde times, and had experience of; that we might be like them both waies, as well in our people, as in our Prieſts. For, euen there <hi>Venite praedicate,</hi> was the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſaying of the people to their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Come and preach to vs ſuch and ſuch things, not as you ſhould, but as wee would haue you, &amp; like beſt to heare of. O my deare brethren, it was neuer well, ſince either the people durſt preſume to giue aime to their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, though neuer ſo ſecretly; or the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſtoopt at the Pulpit dore, to take meaſure of the peoples feete.</p>
               <p>But to returne to the Teachers, becauſe they without controuerſie are the principall in this condemnation, and our Text leadeth me by the hand to taxe them moſt directly; it will be ſaide (perhaps) that ſuch and ſuch falſe Teachers there were, in old time, vnder <hi>Achab</hi> and the reſt, but none now a-daies in the time
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:8954:19"/>of the new Teſtament. That indeede were to imagine a pretie popiſh Common-wealth, where truth had clipther wings, as they ſay, and could no more flie away; the ſpirit being as faſt bound to the Desk, as euer they imagined it was to the Chaire. But, beſides <hi>S. Pauls</hi> heere <hi>If any</hi> teach otherwiſe, <hi>if any,</hi> which extends to all times; beſides that, I ſay, S. <hi>John</hi> tells vs, that euen now many ſpirits are gone abroade into the world, that would be tried before they be truſted, examined afore they bee belieued. S. <hi>Peter</hi> tells vs, <hi>Erant Pſeudo-prophetae,</hi> and <hi>erunt.</hi> 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. (I name the place, becauſe it is moſt obſeruable) that is, there ſhall bee falſe prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, euen as there were falſe prophets, and that <hi>in populo,</hi> among the people: what thinke you of that? Will you haue any more notes of them? that <hi>ſhall priuily bring in damnable Sects, and many ſhall follow their destructions,</hi> and <hi>ſhall make the way of truth to be euill ſpoken of.</hi> And <hi>through couetouſneſſe, they ſhall make merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize of you with fained words, walkers after the fleſh, deſpiſers of gouernment, bolde, ſtanding in their owne conceipt, ſpeaking euill of them that are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n dignity; or if they admire them, it is but for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage ſake, contradicting the things, that in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry truth they knowe not, beguiling the vnstable,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:8954:20"/>forſakers of the right way,</hi> and <hi>turners aſide to a balke of their owne,</hi> after <hi>Balam</hi> the <hi>ſonne of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, that loued the wages of vnrighteouſnes, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> becauſe he ſhould not boaſt too much in his gift of tongue, <hi>his owne Aſſe ſpake vnder him, and a dumb beaſt rebuked the madnes of a ſpeaking Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet. Haec Petri ſunt ferè,</hi> theſe are all out of S. <hi>Peter</hi> for the moſt part, fore-telling the diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous euent of our times.</p>
               <p>And I might add yet more, collected out of the ſame place, which place is ſo worthy for diſcouerie of the ages that were then to come, and are now vndoubtedly come vpon vs, that <hi>S. Iude</hi> hath thought good to repeat almoſt the ſame, in the ſelfe ſame words, after <hi>S. Peter,</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding moreouer a moſt famous &amp; memorable mark, one or two, of his owne, that <hi>S. Peter</hi> had omitted, to demonſtrate the men, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide the queſtion, if it may be, at once, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene vs and them; <hi>Murmurers, Complainers,</hi> and yet <hi>Mockers</hi> too, when they thinke good, and laſt of all <hi>ſeparators. Quòd ſi haec picta vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retis, non dicta audiretis,</hi> now if ſome painter had but drawne theſe things with a coale, not an Apoſtle deſcribed them in colours, as hee hath, could you doubt by which ſide they were to be vnderſtoode?</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:8954:20"/>
               <p> It was our wiſh a long time, as you may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, <hi>vtinam omnis populus,</hi> O that all the people did prophecie, not only <hi>Eldad</hi> and <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dad,</hi> but all the people. Such deſire there was of that holy encreaſe. But ſince we haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, by a coſtly experience, what hurt a <hi>Neo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phytus</hi> doth by ſpeaking in an aſſembly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we would not beleeue S. <hi>Pauls</hi> aduertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: euery ſtripling, nay euery boy, beeing <hi>flabellum concionis,</hi> and <hi>flagellum optimatism,</hi> an inſtrument to ſet the mutinous a gog; and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king this his firſt admittance to popular com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, if he could declaim moſt lewdly, &amp; yet moſt loudly, againſt them that ſcorned, and had good cauſe to ſcorn, to ſet his fathers, or his fathers fathers, with the curres of their flock, as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith. The truth is, now we might ſpare ſom of that ſeed, which hath abounded ſo much to our woful decay, &amp; Iuie-like eaten vp the Tree that ſupported it. <hi>Take back, take backe,</hi> may we ſay with <hi>Moſes,</hi> not your ſtipends, but your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers, vnleſſe they could labor any better a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs. Let goe Church-men, and giue vp your Church-liuings, that you haue with-held an vniuſtice fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. For, not only the people pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh there, where prophecie faileth, which is a ſentence that theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue neuer out of their mouths; but <hi>paſtores multi,</hi> &amp; indeed <hi>ſtulti,</hi> many
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:8954:21"/>ſhepheards, manie, indeede too many to bee good,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 12.10</note> 
                  <hi>diripuerunt vineam meam</hi> (it is Gods owne complaint by <hi>Jeremie</hi>) are the cauſe that our vine lieth ſo waſte &amp; ſo defaced, as it doth at this day.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, in the name of God, if any teach hereafter, let them teach; but not <hi>otherwiſe:</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe they were as good not teach at all. Let the olde ſaying of the Chaldees be verified a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs Chriſtians,
<note place="margin">Mel. Canus in locis.</note> 
                  <hi>Homo quidam ex Iudaeis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit, Sacerdos, neutiquam decipiet nos:</hi> there is a certain ſtranger come to Town, a prieſt I trow, he will not deceiue vs at anie hand. Such opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion they had of the preachers ſinceritie. Let the pulpits be no <hi>Paſquils;</hi> nor the <hi>Moſaicall</hi> trumpet, a trunke to ſhoote pellets at gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and good order: Let no ſlanderous Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters be drawne in the oile of the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, which no water can cleanſe or waſh away; and let a man take heed how he come there to clawe ſides, where no good man enters with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out quaking. For my owne part, I ſay, with <hi>Iacob, Haeceſt Bethel,</hi> this is Gods houſe: and let the ſtone out of the wall witneſſe againſt me, if I decline to partiality, or embrace vntruth.</p>
               <p>But to returne to our Text, If a man teach, <hi>Si quis docet, ſplendidum eſt:</hi> but if he teach other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:8954:21"/>
                  <hi>Si quis diuerſum docet, lubricum est:</hi> tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching is honorable, but otherwiſe is tempting; teaching profiteth, but this otherwiſe marreth and ouerthroweth all. Yet, <hi>Auia Pteridum lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stro loca, nullius ante Trita ſolo;</hi> I would this were a Poets affectation onely, and not a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets: but ſelfe-loue, they ſay, lookes ouer Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits, as wel as ouer meaner places, and priuate glory is made the purchaſe of publique decay. <hi>Abner</hi> calls it play, to haue the young men skirmiſh and flouriſh before him, though it be vvith edge tooles: <hi>Samſons</hi> Foxes make a ſport to toſſe fire-brandes, though it bee to burne corne fields: the skittiſh Kine care not what become of the Arke, which they carie, ſo they may be frisking: and the very confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of tongues and languages, is ſweet meate to ſome, though <hi>Babel</hi> miſſe of her aſpiring purpoſe. Well, I ſay no more but ſo; In <hi>tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching</hi> is not ſo much good, but this <hi>otherwiſe</hi> brings as much euil with it: like the good Figgs and the bad Figges, <hi>Jer.</hi> 24.2. none better than the good, none worſer than the bad: ſo the Teachers of olde times, when religion was firſt reſtored in this our Land, to thoſe that put an <hi>otherwiſe</hi> to their teaching in our daies, and fill all full of ſingularities.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:8954:22"/>
               <p> But to breake off this point, and paſſe on to the next: The ſumme of all is, my deere bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, that you make a difference heereafter betweene Teachers and falſe Teachers, not honouring all promiſcuouſly that beare the name, nor yeelding your eares like a Lute, to be played vpon by euery finger; but diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing wiſely betweene <hi>the Teacher otherwiſe</hi> (as the Text heere hath it, <hi>Jf any teach other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe</hi>) and the Teacher <hi>according to the whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome words,</hi> or according to that <hi>which is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording thereto.</hi> For, as many as walke after this rule (I pray you marke the rule, for it is worth your marking) <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.16. <hi>That Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is nothing, nor vncircumciſion is nothing,</hi> that is, Ceremonie nor no Ceremonie; but the ſubſtantiall <hi>a new Creature,</hi> I ſay, as manie as walke after this rule, <hi>Peace be vpon them,</hi> and <hi>mercie,</hi> and <hi>vpon the Jſrael of God.</hi> But if anie <hi>teach otherwiſe,</hi> oppoſing indifferencie, and oppugning authoritie, <hi>Let no man trouble mee benceforth,</hi> ſaith our Church: for, <hi>I beare in my body the markes of the Lord Jeſus;</hi> and am knowen to be his by the euident prints of his aduerſaries in my fleſh, whom latelie they would haue blowen vp with hell-powder at once. And is it a ſmall thing for them, thus
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:8954:22"/>to fight againſt me from my youth vp, to vexe mee thus continually: but you, euen you, muſt ſet to your hands, and make heauie my yoake, the children of the houſholde, and my owne mothers ſonnes?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>I Come to the third point, with all the ſpeede I can, though I am faine to paſſe by ſome things of moment, vnſpoken-to here; chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie of the Coniunction of the two firſt parts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene themſelues, <hi>Conſent not,</hi> and, <hi>teach o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe.</hi> For, the doore to falſe teaching, is, the not conſenting, or not ſubſcribing at the firſt. Therefore, <hi>S. Paul</hi> puts one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Jf hee conſent,</hi> and, <hi>Jf hee teach otherwiſe.</hi> And yet againe hee puts one before another, as namelie, falſe teaching before refuſing to conſent, becauſe ſome firſt <hi>teach otherwiſe,</hi> and then haue no reaſon to denie <hi>Subſcription,</hi> but onelie becauſe they haue otherwiſe taught. They are loath that a woman ſhould be ſaid to braine <hi>Abimelech</hi> with a mill-ſtone from the wall, loath that lawfull authoritie ſhould cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and curbe their ſtubborne fancie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:8954:23"/>
               <p>THe third point is, <hi>The Rule of Triall, the Square of truth,</hi> for iudging of matters that depend in controuerſie. A moſt liuely one, and a moſt abſolute one, that the Apoſtle here giues, if I miſdeeme not; conſiſting of <hi>2.</hi> parts; one, the <hi>wholeſome words of Christ or of godlineſſe,</hi> the other, <hi>The Doctrine that is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thereto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And firſt, to ſpeake of the wholſom words; I cannot heere diſcourſe in the praiſe of <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie,</hi> as gladly I would haue done at another time, how that it is the onely wholſom ſcience, when all is done; others are but for gloſſe and for ornament, hanging gold and iewels vpon our apparrell, as <hi>Saul</hi> did vpon the Iſraelites garments. <hi>Abillis enim ſalubritas quaedam,</hi> or not ſo much as that; but <hi>ingenua animi delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiotantùm: ab hac ſanitas &amp; vita ipſa petitur:</hi> they put bloud into our face, like the <hi>Aliptae,</hi> amend our colour and our complexion a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; but this like the Phyſician cheriſhes our ſparke, maintaines our life, whom therefore neceſſitie her ſelfe compels vs to honour.</p>
               <p>And ſurely, without theſe wholſom words, all that growes abroade in the greene fields of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:8954:23"/>Philoſophie, it is but <hi>toxicum,</hi> but euen meer poiſon, and <hi>mors in olla, mors in olla,</hi> death is in the pott, we may ſay, where that but enters. <hi>Eliſaeus</hi> his ſalt only ſweetens the broth, which a ſtrange root hath made diſtaſtable, while the young ſchollers, and children of the Prophets doo not diſcerne vvhat they gather: and <hi>Moſes</hi> his wood, that is the Goſpell of Chriſt Ieſus, <hi>lignum vitae,</hi> and <hi>lignum crucis,</hi> reliſhes the <hi>Marah</hi> of Gentile learning, whoſe waters are bitter, and end in deſperation, without ſuch mixture. Therfore S. <hi>Hierome</hi> was buffited by an Angell, for ſtudying heathen Authors too much; but, an Angell made S. <hi>John</hi> not giue ouer the booke of wholſome wordes, that hee brought him, till he had eaten and ſwallowed it downe.</p>
               <p>But, as <hi>J</hi> ſaid, I may not ſtand hereupon; no, nor yet vpon the 1. part of this rule, <hi>The words of Christ,</hi> and that ſame <hi>hunc audite,</hi> heare you him; which was ſpoken when all the reſt were vaniſhed and diſappeared out of the Mount, both <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> &amp; <hi>Elias;</hi> that we might knowe his ſingular prerogatiue ouer the Church, wherin neither <hi>Moſes,</hi> nor <hi>Elias,</hi> nor <hi>Peter</hi> nor any communicate vvith him. Hovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, ſtill vve muſt remember, that there is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:8954:24"/>
                  <hi>audite</hi> left for ſomebody elſe too, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>heare you him,</hi> though in their rank and in their place, as, <hi>qui vos audit, &amp;c.</hi> he that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth you heareth me, ſpoken of the Prelats &amp; Paſtors of the Church, that ſhall ſucceed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually to the end of the World; and <hi>ſi non au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit eccleſiam,</hi> if hee heare not the Church in in her determinations, let him be counted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the heathen, and the Infidels, let him loſe the verie right that hee hath of his Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome. For ſo ſaith the ſecond part of this rule heere in my Text, <hi>And the doctrine accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to godlineſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For perſwading wherof the better, &amp; that we ſeem not to open a floodgate to popery, to ruſh in vpon vs all amain, it may pleaſe you to diſtinguiſh two kindes of <hi>Verities,</hi> which holy ſcripture hath diſtinguiſhed long before vs, in the Ep to the <hi>Col.</hi> 2.5. Som <hi>of Faith,</hi> ſom <hi>of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi> Now the verities of faith are ſo plentifully ſet downe in the Olde and New Teſtaments, as he addeth to his own plagues, that ſhal pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to add one iot therto. For the wil of an or dinary man, that dead is; no man dareth to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terline (ſaith the Apoſtle) how much leſs then his, that witneſſed a good confeſſion vnder <hi>Po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Pilate</hi> &amp; ſealed his Couenant with his own
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:8954:24"/>blood? Yet ſom do, it cannot be denied. In this net ſticks the Boar of <hi>Rome</hi> at this day, &amp; is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with more <hi>Anathemaes</hi> for his preſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, than <hi>Abſolon</hi> was with darts hanging between heauen &amp; earth in the tree: though the beagels of the ſecte, miſtaking their ſent, leaue him to purſue vs with open volly &amp; crie. The books of the two Teſtaments they are all in all, for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of our faith &amp; demonſtration impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable; the two pillars to conduct vs out of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> into <hi>Canaan,</hi> one of ſmoke, dark like the Old Teſtament, another of fire, bright like the New; the two great lights, that God reared in the firmament and aduanced, and yet the ſun to rule the day, the moone the night, ſo much clearer is our planet than was the Fathers; the two Cherubins that face the Mercy ſeat with mutuall counterview, now the Mercie ſeat is Chriſt, whom the two Teſtaments equally ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue &amp; demonſtrate; the two ſpies loaded with a cluſter of grapes moſt delicious to ghoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taſte; the two Oliue branches that ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord of the whole earth; the two mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones that neuer Tyrant yet tooke to pawne from the poore church; the two dugges of the Spouſe, the 2. ſticks of the widow, the 2. wings of the Eagle, the tvvo mites of Gods treaſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:8954:25"/>exceeding all that was caſt in before or beſides, the bagg that hath both old and nevv in it, able to make a Scribe learned towarde the heavenly Kingdom. O bevvare hovv you diſparage the ſufficiency of ſcripture for mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of faith. O bevvare hovv you detracte from the fulneſs therof, <hi>cuius plenitudinem ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro</hi> (ſayth <hi>Tertullian</hi>) vvhoſe abſolute perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I admire at my very heart, and vvorſhip vvith my face bovved dovvn to the ground.</p>
               <p>But, there are other matters of <hi>Order</hi> beſide thoſe, vvhich though they be far leſs in valuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on than the former, yet their littleneſs is not to be drovvned in the others greatneſs. <hi>Et haec facere oportuit, &amp; illa non negligere</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour) theſe things you ought to doo, and yet not deſpiſe thoſe. <hi>Faith, Faith</hi> (I ſay) as great as ſhe is, cannot maintaine her ſelf, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the rules of good Order, in any ſtate or ctedit, nomore than the king can conſiſt vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the fielde that is tilled, as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſayth, And theſe things are not expreſſed in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure; they are not. For neither neede they, neither could they; they need not, becauſe ſo obuious; and they could not, becauſe ſo num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brous: but, <hi>Reliqua cum venero ordinabo,</hi> ſayth the Apoſtle, <hi>Other things J will ſet in order
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:8954:25"/>when J come,</hi> theſe things muſt be ordered, as they may be, by occaſion. <hi>Dauid</hi> did not all things during his life, as he meant ſhould be done in proceſs of time; but he gaue order to <hi>Salomon</hi> to ſee to the execution of them by leaſure, becauſe he was a wiſe man; as himſelf ſaith, <hi>thou art wiſe and knoweſt what is fitte to be done: therfore, after my departure, ſee that thou doe thus and thus, &amp;c.</hi> So, the Chriſtian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate and Regent of the Church, whome God hath indued with the ſpirit of wiſdome, and with whom he is aſſiſtant, to the conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the world, ſupplies in this caſe, that which was no imperfection for the ſcripture to leaue out, but rather an impoſſibilitie for the ſcripture to comprehend. I dare be bolde to ſay it, the ſcripture which is Chriſts letter of of loue, penned to his Church, as S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſweetly calls it, muſt haue exceeded not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>menſuram Epiſtolae,</hi> the meaſure of ſo ſmall a compoſition, which ſhould neuer fill more than the left hand of the Reader, if we belieue <hi>Seneca;</hi> but euen ſwollen in quantity aboue the Popes <hi>Decretals,</hi> which LVTHER of zeale burnt in the market place, (they were ſo irk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and ſo tedious) if all things of this nature had been to be regiſtred &amp; ingroſſed in them.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:8954:26"/>Fonts, plates, pewes, belles, deskes, can you want them? can you ſpare them? yea Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches &amp; Chappels too, by your leaue, which the Apoſtles had none, nor diuers ſucceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s after the Apoſtles; and therefore the <hi>Browniſts</hi> like good honeſt fellows pull them down, as faſt as they can, by vertue of this principle, &amp; neuer diſſemble for the matter.</p>
               <p>If al things were written that our Sauior did, ſaith S. <hi>John,</hi> I ſuppoſe the world woulde not containe the books: but I may ſay, if all things were written, that are lawfully incident to the particular worſhip &amp; ſeruice of God, a world of worlds would not containe the books, that ſhould conteine them. Yet are not our Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies therfore ſo many, that they ſhould op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs vs with their multitude &amp; load, as they vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iuſtly cauil at vs; they are in number as few as poſſibly can bee in a Church, in ſubſtance as grave, in choiſe as diſcreet, in ſight as comly, in obſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as eaſy, in ſignificance as natural &amp; correſpondent: but though we haue confined our ſelues to paucitie for good reſpects, yet the thing it ſelf in nature is wonderfull broad.</p>
               <p>Now let the ſcoffers of this our doctrine ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in their likeneſs, &amp; ſhew their faces, if they dare for ſhame. They traduce our cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:8954:26"/>&amp; blaze them to the world for blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers: one becauſe he ſaith <hi>Chriſt</hi> is not <hi>the ſole Lawe-giuer of his Church,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In their Challenge to Diſputat.</note> another about the raweneſſe of the primitiue times compared with ours; though it cannot be denied but in many reſpects the church hath bin bettered as well as empaired by continuance. Separate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while your ſelues from preiudice, and let not the captiouſneſs of tearms trouble you, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider if you can the naked truth. Why ſhould this ſeeme ſtrange in your eares, that Chriſt is <hi>not the only Lawgiuer of his Church,</hi> in the ſenſe that we deny it, or how can it euer be avowed for true in the ſenſe that they obtrude it? Are there no lawes, thinke you, to be obſerued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong chriſtian men &amp; women, touching mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of church and of Religion, but ſuch as Chriſt hath eſtabliſhed and promulged with his own mouth? Certainlie, I wil produce no hidden arguments, certainly I will not ſearch the depths, as they ſay, nor ſcowr the bottoms for this matter; I will alleage no more than you all know, &amp; are all able to iudge of, and yet I wil conclude the thing in queſtion; that you may ſee the difference between <hi>the wholſome words of Chriſt the Lord,</hi> as our Text here hath it, and <hi>the doctrine which is according to godlines.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:8954:27"/>
               <p> If any of you ſhould commaund your ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, or your ſon, to carry a Bible with them to Church vpon the Sondaies, vnder paine of your heauie diſpleaſure if they did not, doe you think it were a law that might be broken, or no? A law doubtleſs it were, as being taxed with puniſhment vppon the offendor. Your ſelues would think it fit to be kept, not fit to be broken. And yet it is in matter of Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice and Religion. For, let no man deceiue himſelf my deere brethren, not willingly miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſter vs; there was none of vs euer placed ſo much Religion in a garment, as you doe in a Booke. And yet CHRIST neuer badde it, and it is left free; for all ſinne not, you muſt think, that come to Church without their Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, though they can read.</p>
               <p>Winde your ſelues now out of this net, as well as you can, which is no net, but a ſounde and ſubſtantial confutation, ſpecially you that delight in ambuſh, as <hi>the twelue reaſons,</hi> and intorteled Syllogiſmes. Or, if you ſay that Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded vs to ſearch the Scriptures; well, though that doth not enforce, that wee ſhould carrie them to the Church, to euerie Lecture, or ſermon, with vs; yet, let the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſuppoſition hold, but in <hi>Lidleyes prayer
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:8954:27"/>Booke,</hi> or <hi>Bradfords Meditations,</hi> or ſome ſuch like, and then ſee what you can ſay to it; whether you will allowe your ſeruant or your ſonne to croſſe your commandement in ſuch a reſpect or not. Neither againe maie you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept that the bringing of the Bible helpes to edifie, the ceremonies not: for the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies edifie too in their place and order (I will not now compare them with a lay mans Bible) and the queſtion is not ſo much touching edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication (if you mark it) as whether they may be vrged vppon the conſciences of beleeuers by lawe, though they be neuer ſo apt in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to edifie.</p>
               <p>How then is it my deare Brethren and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of this Cittie? may your prentiſes be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, your children compelled, by your priuate law-giuing authoritie, thus and thus to demeane themſelues in Gods ſeruice &amp; vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, without anie diſparagement to the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame Law-giuer, and may not they whoſe iuriſdiction is ſo farre greater than yours, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt the ſame ouer them that they gouerne? Maie the Houſholder do this in his houſe, and not the king in his kingdomes? Maie the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the mother, and not Gods Liefte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt and Deputie generall? Naie, maie the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:8954:28"/>
                  <hi>Paedant</hi> in his flock and not the <hi>Prince?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For to ſay the father commands but a few, and the maiſter a fewe, the King all the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters &amp; Preachers of the Land, is an oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on more fit for you to make than for me to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue, or rather ſo vnfit for me to remoue, that indeed it is not fit for you to make: the kings authoritie iuſtly ſtretching farther, why? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the limits of his Realms are wider; and if he allow you to be kings in your houſholds, you muſt allow him to be a houſholder in his kingdom, at the leaſt.</p>
               <p>Again, to ſay that the one are Miniſters and Preachers, the other but children &amp; ſeruants, is as vain. For, if chriſtian libertie muſt not be infringed in binding miniſters &amp; preachers, no more may it be infringed in binding children, and ſeruants; &amp; if Eccleſiaſticall Canons wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the priuiledge that came by Chriſts blood, ſo do domeſticall: we know no ſuch prerogatiue of one aboue another in theſe kind of cauſes, euery mans conſcience is as free and as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touchable as anothers before God,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 3.11</note> one price was paid for all.</p>
               <p>I omitte many things, that might be allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, to make this fort not onely ſtrong but inuincible. The Church wee ſay, may make
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:8954:28"/>lavves, and not Chriſt only. She that may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale them, ſhe may make them:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 15</note> The Church repealed the law of abſtinence from ſtrangled and bloud, when ſhe ſaw fit time, &amp; cancelled that which the Apoſtles by the inſtinct of the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ghoſt had enacted, but enacted without any limitation of time. The ſame I might ſaie of the kiſs of Charitie vſed in Church, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded in Scripture,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12</note> 
                  <hi>Greete yee one another with an holy kiſs;</hi> now laied aſide with as much maturitie as at firſt it was brought in with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe. The ſame of widows to be fedd by the Church, an Apoſtolique ſanction, and yet now not ſo much as called for once, by them that profeſſe the reſtauration of the golden age to the quick, ſo as we ſhall not haue a pinn nor a pegge miſſing, as they ſay, in the great worke of their ſecond Tabernacle.</p>
               <p>I might proceede to more.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Calv. Instit. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 8. <hi>ſect.</hi> 32. <hi>et</hi> 34. <hi>Chemn. in loc. Com. p.</hi> 2. <hi>de</hi> 3. <hi>praec. Vrſin. in catech. in</hi> 4. <hi>pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Bellarm. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin. Sanct. l.</hi> 2 <hi>c</hi> 7. <hi>vbi. Auguſt. Irena<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>et Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam citat in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andem ſent. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſ. Rom. et Chapeaville in eum locum Cat.</hi>
                  </note> The Sabbath that wee celebrate euerie ſeauenth daie, is it not of the Church and her conſtitution meer? The diſcourſe were impertinent but the * con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of writers maie goe for proof in the mean time, and the places are verie pregnant, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.5. <hi>Coloſsi.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.5. with the like, beſides a troupe of reaſons that perſwade that way.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:8954:29"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Judas Maccabaeus</hi> inſtituted a Feaſt, by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of his place, and of his authoritie among the Iewes, and increaſed the number of Feaſts that God had appointed to his people. Yet our Sauiour ſanctified it by his bleſſed pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; thought it no diſparagement to his ſole law-giuing. <hi>John.</hi> 10.22.</p>
               <p>The Muſicke of the Temple, that <hi>Dauid</hi> brought in, we read it approoued, wee neuer read it commaunded. What ſome thinke they maie gather out of obſcure conſequences, I regarde not a ruſh: If euer it come to triall I can ſaie as much, why <hi>Dauid</hi> ſhould doo it of his owne head, as by anie ſpeciall commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, for ought that appears by Scripture: Yet, the high Lawe-giuer was not diſpleaſed with it. And, if happilie theſe men had beene by the ſame <hi>Dauid,</hi> when he danced naked be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Arke, they would haue greatlie bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him, for bringing a nevv ſeruice into the Church, for ſomuch as dancing was no where preſcribed; and chid him for affecting naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in Gods worſhip: which, they might doo with better colour than they can chide vs for our apparell. So is our caſe one with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: ſo are the actions of the greateſt Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arches ſubiect to the ſame reprehenſion of the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:8954:29"/>ſcornefull, that our practices are heer at home; and the Land is not yet rid of her <hi>Micholls.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ionadab</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Rechab</hi> interdicted his ſonnes the vſe of wine, for all their life time; and God commended his ſeuere Law-giuing. Yet, <hi>Jonadabs</hi> authority came ſhort of the roi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and we haue no ſuch ſtrictneſs enioined vs, as is the abſtinence of wine for a mans whole life time. The braſen Serpent was Gods ovvn ordinance; <hi>Ezechias</hi> as King brake it in pieces, when he ſavv cauſe. No direction from God, no entercourſe of the Prophets moouing him thereto: yet, his fact is famous throughout all poſterities. Lo, the weapon that they thruſt at vs ſo often in vain, mortally retorted vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their own breſts. Laſtly, the <hi>K.</hi> of <hi>Nineueh</hi> cloathed cattle in ſackcloth, a thing more monſtrous &amp; vncouth to behold, than anie ſurplice vpon a mans backe; Yea further, made children and beaſts refraine from meat, a faſting for which he had no foundation in ſcripture. Was it ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore euer a-whit the leſs accepted? <hi>J</hi> trow not: God was appeaſed with it, God turned awaie his wrath vpon it: we put no ſuch confidence in our conſtitutions, albeit the ceremonies haue their vſe.</p>
               <p>The antient Fathers, S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in his 5. booke
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:8954:30"/>
                  <hi>de Baptiſmo.</hi> 9. chap. and <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his book of the ſame argument, agree in this that God gaue no direction to S. <hi>John Baptist</hi> of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing in particular, but onely in generall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed him to baptiſe; the rites and the faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons he was to add himſelf at his owne pleaſure. And therefore it is called, ſay they, the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm of <hi>Iohn,</hi> as being his own for the moſt part. Yet heer was no iniury to Chriſt the ſole Law-giuer, or elſe he ſhould haue been ſure to haue heard of it. To conclude in a word, we neuer read in all the Scripture, that Chriſt is <hi>the onely Law-giuer</hi> of his church: and yet if we ſhould, we haue that ſmal vnderſtanding with vs, as to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſter it no otherwiſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the only Teacher, &amp; yet other Teachers; the only Magiſtrate, &amp; yet other Magiſtrates; (for we muſt deſire the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now that we may haue no <hi>Anabaptiſm</hi> to trouble vs in our arg. whatſoer they thinke, or whatſoer they wold do at another time:) ſo the only <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiger</hi> of the houſe of <hi>Dauid,</hi> &amp; yet the Church hath hir keies too of no ſmall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequence; the only foſter-father of his flock, &amp; yet many nur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſing fathers &amp; many nurſing mothers (God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſe the number) of his poore Church; whoſe milk is diſciplin, whoſe diet is ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſure, whoſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment is nurture &amp; good laws. No doubt the ſoueraign drownes not the ſubordinate, in all
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:8954:30"/>theſe &amp; the like inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces. But ſimple folks may be blear'd with tearms, &amp; the one eied man ruf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles it they ſay among the ſtark blind. Forgery ceaſes in the wiſe mans preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. So much ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore concerning that. Another thing they carpe at in the doctrine of our men: which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs to the place that I now handle, I wil ſpeak a word or twain vnto, &amp; ſo an end. It is for ſaying the Church cannot er in defining about ceremonies, or any ſuch matter of order arbitrary, &amp; indifferent, define ſhe how ſhe wil. Truly to enquire what the Church may doe, in vtmoſt extent, without poſſibility of ſliding in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to error, is a thing more meet for ſchooles than pulpits, &amp; to exerciſe great iudgements than to tickle curious eares. Yet thus much as a ſchoolman I wil be bold to vndertake to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min by the way, that forſomuch as things indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t are exceeding diuers in their own nature, &amp; many lawfull that are not expedient, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Apoſtls ſaying; yet ſuppoſing the aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the ſpirit of God in ruling his Church, which is rather Chriſtian to belieue than to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ride or to denie, the church ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not er, define ſhe howſoeuer in ſuch caſes: &amp; again, not ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſo, yet ſhe cannot er dangerouſly, howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ſhee determine touching ſuch matters. I ſay <hi>determine;</hi> for in preferring the ceremonies
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:8954:31"/>before the ſubſtantialls by waie of obſeruation ſhe maie erre, as the Church of the Iewes did, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God often reprehends <hi>eo nomine;</hi> &amp; again I ſay <hi>the Church,</hi> for if the Papiſts haue erred e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in deuiſing ſome of their ceremonies, yet that is ſince their ſynagogue loſt indeede the honor of that title. So much alſo briefly may ſerue for that.</p>
               <p>The laſt thing that I will note out of our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries exceptions compared with the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of this preſent place, is that which the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of <hi>the challenge to diſputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> hath ſet down in a certaine place, much (as I remember) to this purpoſe;</p>
               <p>That, if we in our opinions, which we main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine about Ceremonies, vſed in the Church of England, as they are at this day, be right, then our departure from the papiſts cannot be iuſtified, and the Pope with his adherents, nay Chriſt the Sonne of God, and his heauenly truth in them, hath had great iniurie to bee ſo long novve relinquiſhed vppon no other grounds.</p>
               <p>Yea they farther profeſs, that themſelues wil becom papiſts, and Ieſuits (&amp; what not?) if we can but quit our ſelues in the controuerſie. O ſpeech worthy the authors of it! O ſpeech moſt
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:8954:31"/>vnworthy the eares of any chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lô ſpeech than which the diuell of hell could neuer haue roared out a more viperous, nor a more dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable one, aboue ground. Let it be noted, I would wiſh you, &amp; noted again, with a pen of Diamond, in tables of braſſe, to ſhewe the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the ſect for euer, that, when they would reuoke it, they may not be able. For, what thinke you my deere brethren &amp; Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men of this place? Is it matter of <hi>Order</hi> that we haue left <hi>Rome</hi> for, or matter of <hi>Faith?</hi> Is it matter of ceremony, or matter of ſubſtance? Is it a ſtraw, or a block, nay a great beame? Is it a gap and a buſh, or a countermure of ſtone, and trench vnpaſſable, that diuides vs from them? ſo great, as we cannot imagine that was euer greater, which ſometime diuided <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> from the rich man in hell.</p>
               <p>And yet beholde; worſhipping of Images, adoring of reliques, inuoking of Angels, buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Churches to Saints, ſacrificing for the ſinnes of quicke and dead with a Wafer-cake, treading downe Kings, the Deputies of God, from their throne of Maieſtie, to ſet vp a foxie Intruder in their roome, whom all ages haue acknowledged their vaſſall; taking away Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, mangling of Sacraments, licenſing Stews,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:8954:32"/>condemning mariage, vvrapping vp your ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, and the obſequies of your conſcience in the ſtrange liuorie of an vnknowen tongue, ſelling pardons for ſixe pence, ſoule-eaſe for money, heauen at pleaſure, oppoſing the flax of our tranſitorie deedes to the vnpartiall fire of the heauenly righteouſneſſe, mingling the bloud of Martyrs, that I ſay not of Traytors, with the bloud of the Lambe of God, ſpotleſſe and immaculate, which onely taketh away the ſinnes of the world, which onely quencheth the rage of the wrath to come, which onely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bateth the edge of his fathers iuſtice, and the ſword <hi>Cherubicall</hi> that glitters afore <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> theſe thinges are now no cauſe to leaue <hi>Rome</hi> for, by our mens doctrine; or at leaſt no more cauſe, then ſurplice or no ſurplice, geſture or no geſture, ceremonie or no ceremonie, preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterie or Biſhopdome amount to heere at home betweene our ſelues. But as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſo I ſay once againe: Let it bee noted, <hi>J</hi> would wiſh you, and noted moſt heede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, to ſhewe the diſpoſition of the ſect for euer, that when they would reuoke it vpon better deliberation, they may not bee able. So much alſo concerning that. For <hi>J</hi> doubt not, I, but your knowledge is ſatisfied, and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:8954:32"/>their phrenzie diſcouered ſufficientlie heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>J</hi> ſhould proceed from hence, to ſome of their obiections, as weake as water, and as vaine as vanitie it ſelfe vpon the weights: As, <hi>Mardocheus</hi> his refuſing to riſe to <hi>Haman,</hi> though the King commaunded it, will-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, mans ordinances, <hi>Whatſoeuer is not of faith, is ſinne;</hi> therefore we muſt haue expreſſe Scripture for all that wee doe, ſhewes of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill would be abandoned, Reliques of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie layed aſide, no conformitie with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleeuers, and the like. For, who euer roſe vp in contradiction againſt the Church, but had a <hi>ſcriptum est</hi> of his ſide, and ſomewhat to ſay for himſelfe? Yet with ſuch ſtuffe as theſe (a thing lamentable to be ſpoken) they vſually ſucke the bloud of your ſoules, and peruert many from the right way. But I muſt make haſte to that which is behinde: and to ſay truth, whom the former poſitiue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmations will not ſatisfie, hee will bee lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle the better for diſſoluing theſe and the like their cobweb-obiections. I haue done it often, moſt often, in other places; I pray you once giue mee leaue to paſſe them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer heere.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:8954:33"/>
               <p> So much of the third point, <hi>The rule of trial,</hi> or, <hi>the ſquare of truth:</hi> which conſiſts not onely in <hi>the wholſome words of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> but in the <hi>Doctrines, that are commenced and framed according thereto.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Contra Pſychi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cos.</note> For, as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaies moſt ſweetly, <hi>Non tantùm ſeruire debeo Domino meo, ſed adulari;</hi> wee muſt not doe all that we doe of Iniunction, but we may honour God with our freeſt inuention. And <hi>S. Pauls</hi> limitation is very large, and no way thralled to the narrowneſſe of thoſe precincts that they imagine, <hi>Philippians,</hi> 4.8. <hi>Whatſoeuer thinges are honest, whatſoeuer thinges are iust, whatſoeuer thinges are pure, whatſoeuer thinges pertaine to loue, and are well reported of, thoſe doe,</hi> and the <hi>GOD of peace ſhall bee with you.</hi> Doe you but marke the promiſe that <hi>the God of peace</hi> ſhall bee vvith vs? vvhom theſe men vvould ſo faine keepe out of our Land, and baniſh, as they ſay, by head and ſhoulders. O the ſweet maske of <hi>Peace</hi> to appeare in! O the gracious forme of peace to maske in! Let him alway appeare to me in that forme: let him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way preſent himſelfe to me in that ſhape. Not in fire nor in tempeſt: for, in them the Lord was not, ſaith the Scripture: but in the ſoft and ſtill vvinde. <hi>The God of peace ſhall be with you.</hi>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:8954:33"/>This was the promiſe: but now mark the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept alſo, I pray you: <hi>Whatſoeuer things are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, whatſoeuer things are iuſt, whatſoeuer things are pure, whatſoeuer things pertaine to loue, and are well reported of, thoſe doe. Jf there be any vertue, if there be any praiſe.</hi> O notable accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation of the Apoſtles pen to our times! For, what more <hi>honest,</hi> than that which can be charged with no crime, but onely iealouſie &amp; ſuſpicion refuſeth! So are our Ceremonies. What more <hi>iust,</hi> than that which lawfull au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cthoritie hath eſtabliſhed, and thoſe lippes that harbour an oracle, ratified and approued? Yet ſo are our ceremonies. What more <hi>pure,</hi> than that which is refined in the fornace, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from the dregs of all ancient ſuperſtition? yet ſo are our ceremonies. What more <hi>pertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nining to loue,</hi> than the pledges of combination betweene the Miniſters of one Kingdom, like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly alſo to draw the aduerſaries to an vnion? yet this is the verie nature &amp; ſcope of our ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies. As for <hi>praiſe,</hi> and <hi>vertue,</hi> and <hi>good report,</hi> and ſuch like, the beſt, &amp; the beſt-iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented will eaſilie allow it them: the worſt I knowe depraue them, whoſe iudgment makes them neuer the worſe for all that. And where the former titles goe before, as <hi>honestie, purity,</hi>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:8954:34"/>and the like; theſe latter muſt needs follow of their owne accord, they may not bee parted. Wherefore, if your delight be in the God of peace, ſtriue not againſt ſuch thinges: as for thoſe that put them from them ſo violently, they ſhew plainely that peace is not their ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king. But, ſo much ſhall ſerue, as I ſaid, for the third point generall of the Text.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>THe fourth point remaines, which is, <hi>the indifferencie of the parties,</hi> offending a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that which wee haue formerly deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, of <hi>conſenting to the words that are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to godlineſſe,</hi> and, <hi>not teaching otherwiſe. If any man;</hi> be hee who he will be, learned or lewd, Clarke or Lay-man, ſpirituall or tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, holy or profane, one or many, For there is no riſing vp againſt Iuſtice for reſpects, and <hi>Salomons</hi> ſword ſtrikes vnpartiall where it hits; <hi>Vlyſſes</hi> muſt not ſwarue for <hi>Telemachus</hi> in the furrow, and a Iudge muſt haue eares to ſcanne the cauſes, but no eyes to diſcern the perſons. <hi>If any.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet the multitude cries out; The good men, the purer ſort, the preciſer ſort, of great
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:8954:34"/>parts, of great paines, they are ſilenced, they are depriued. <hi>Parúmne Sanctus Paulus,</hi> vvas <hi>S. Paul,</hi> thinke you, an Apoſtle, or no? Did he ſpeake by the inſtinct of the holy Ghoſt, or no? that hath ſo damped the clamours of the iniudiciall multitude, and checked their fond exceptions long afore-hand, with his <hi>If any,</hi> if any man; be hee who he will be, looke not to his perſon, truſt not to thine eye, make no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, remember the Church, and the peace of the Church, the coate of Chriſt, nay the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of Chriſt, <hi>Pereat vnus potius quàm vnitas,</hi> and, <hi>Nulla charitas ad eam charitatem qua ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtringimur Eccleſiae:</hi> Let <hi>Saul</hi> take heede how hee ſpare <hi>Agag</hi> for pretexts, and ſlay the meagrer and the wretcheder of the Kine and Cattle, paſſing by the fairer for his owne luſts ſake.</p>
               <p>But becauſe they doe ſo aggrauate the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter againſt vs, in regard of their worth; we will way the reſpects that they moſt truſt to, in due ballance, and ſee what in extreamitie they may challenge at our handes. I am loath, I confeſſe, to enter into this kinde of comparatiue conflict. For, I haue learned of <hi>Aristotle</hi> not to be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ethic.</hi> 4.</note> but the importance of the cauſe, and Saint <hi>Pauls
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:8954:35"/>If any,</hi> ouer-rules my diſpoſition for this once.</p>
               <p>Three things they moſt beard vs with, their life, their learning, their labours. For they are honeſt men, as they ſay, painfull men, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found men. And if we goe to leuie them now by the Tribes and the families, and at laſt by the head and the poll, to ſee if they be all aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to this report that goes of them, or no; wee are tolde afore-hand very mannerly forſooth, not all without exception for life, but ſome; not all ſo deeply learned, but ſome; not all ſo painefull nor induſtrious in their vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but ſome. And ſo we haue heere in effect <hi>beſtiam pharmacopolae,</hi> that <hi>Julian</hi> the Pelagian vpbraided S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> with, the beaſt that the Apothecarie promiſed his patient of wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vertue, which, afore morning was com, had eaten vp her ſelfe. For, if onely ſome be thus approued for life amongſt themſelues, what then ſhal we ſay of the other more obnoxious? and yet beholde, they all crie out to haue the vices, and the ſcandalls of the Cleargie refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. And if onely ſome be thus eſteemed for learning among themſelues, what then ſhall we ſay of the other ſort of inſufficient? and yet they all require a learned Miniſterie. And if
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:8954:35"/>onely ſome be ſo famous for paines taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelues, what then ſhall wee ſay of the other idle Drones? and yet all crie out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt lazie labourers, and would haue Hiue, and Bees, and hony, &amp; all, giuen ouer to them to ſucke.</p>
               <p>Doe you not ſee, beloued, by theſe things moſt clearely, the beginning, the proceedings, and the end of the whole faction? Set on foote no doubt, by ſome, that thought well of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and perhaps had cauſe ſo to doe, if they could haue done it, within any good meaſure, or compaſſe; afterward helped forward by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that had no ſuch deſert of their owne to raiſe them; yet thought they would bee follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers of the Campe, lending their hands, and their names with the foremoſt, partly for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, and partly for hope of ſpoile and booty? at laſt the poore people caried away with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bubs &amp; imaginations, hearing them not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to vaunt of their vertues, but to crake of their forces, and that by the hundreds now and the thouſands? Whereas, of all theſe thinges there is no one true, as I haue ſhewed, or that they dare ſtand to, in ſtrict tearmes; and yet if all were as true as they make ſhewe for, yet number preuailes not againſt the right, as S.
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:8954:36"/>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> here hath it, <hi>If any man,</hi> whoſoeuer he be, or how many ſoeuer they be; and excellent gifts bind to excellent modeſtie, giue no leaue to men to be mutinous.</p>
               <p>You ſee beloued, by theſe delaies, how loath I am to come to the ſtricter ſcanning of their three-folde Comparatiue, their life, their lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, their labours, that they beare down ours ſo mightily withall, as they think. Yet ſomwhat muſt be ſaid, I cannot dwell long vpon it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I come to it againſt my will.</p>
               <p>Firſt, for their life, that they magnifie ſo much. Howbeit, I would counſell them to ſpare this plea, or let ſome other ſpeake it for them. <hi>Alienus laudet te non os tuum,</hi> it would ſound better in their neighbours mouthes. Surely, vertue neuer dwelt at this ſigne; ſurely ſhe is no <hi>Dinah</hi> that romes abroad to ſee, and to be ſeene of the daughters of the Country; but rather an <hi>Elizabeth</hi> that hides her ſelfe ſixe moneths together breeding childe, and that ſo famous a childe as <hi>S. Iohn Baptist</hi> was; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther euer did religion write vpon her poſts, <hi>My houſe is the houſe of prayer.</hi> It is no ſpeach of a contrite heart, <hi>Stand farther from me, J am pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer than thou;</hi> but, <hi>depart from me Lord, for J am a ſinner.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:8954:36"/>
               <p> Beſides, this is moſt certaine, no vice euer ſhewed her face without a vizard yet, in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, if ſhe could hide it; hypocriſie muſt lead in hereſie by the hand, and vſher it, and make way for it, like the Damoſell that led <hi>S. Peter</hi> into the high Prieſts Hall, euery body ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horres it, if it appeare as it is. But, <hi>Speculum conſulitur,</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Cyprian, cur? niſi quia timet ne ſit ipſa,</hi> ſhe conſults with her looking-glaſſe, till that at leaſt ſay ſhee is faire. Boyes with nuts, like the Jndians with rattles, or ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie toyes; and men many times are caried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with ſhewes, with gloſes, and profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. As if <hi>Iudas</hi> kiſt not where hee meant to kill, or olde ſhooes transform'd a Gibeonite, or <hi>Jezabels</hi> paint were anie better then the plaiſter of a leaprous countenance, that lur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vnderneath. Therefore wee reade of Woolues that ſhall come in Sheepes clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinges, therefore vvee reade of <hi>Satan,</hi> dreſt like an Angell of light. Falſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets haue vvorne rough garments next their fleſh, as well as the good, and <hi>Pelagius,</hi> was as ſtrict a man for life, as hee vvas re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate concerning the faith. Did not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout women reſiſt S. <hi>Paul?</hi> ſo <hi>J</hi> ſay, de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> women, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.15. and wee heare th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> theſe
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:8954:37"/>haue the like on their ſide: no meruaile. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are the Monkes of later times yet out of our mindes, with all their painted holineſſe &amp; goodly ſhewes, whoſe ſoules, if it were not an error of <hi>Pythagoriſme,</hi> I would not ſticke to ſay had come to take vp their manſions once more in theſe mens bodies. Pardon vs, pardon vs, if we yeeld not to a ſecond gull, ſpecially ſerued vpon vs ſo freſhlie in the ſame kinde, and giue vs leaue to diſtinguiſh between <hi>Samuel,</hi> and the Diuel, whom the Witch of <hi>Endor</hi> hath ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in his mantle; ſo farre forth like him, if you wil, but that hee is known by his aſcending out of the earth.</p>
               <p>I am loath, I proteſt, to diſcouer <hi>Noah,</hi> wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing in his ſhame, and drunken fits, though their boiſterous enormities cannot make them to iudge mildelie of others infirmities. But what thinke you? ſhall we call that mortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which wee are ſure to finde, not in the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſterie embracing the duſt, nor yet with the Doctors diſputing in the Temple; but ſitting vpper moſt at belly cheare, and at Feaſts? ſhall we call that auſteritie, which fawnes, and crou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and tells newes for a meale? courage and fortitude, that reiects tythes and properties, to graze vpon a beneuolence? contentment with
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:8954:37"/>a little, which hath a hooke in the end of it like a <hi>Harpago,</hi> and picks as many purſes by day, as a thiefe takes praies in the night ſeaſon? humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that ſhaking of the Biſhops Iuriſdiction, would now be the onelie Pope in the Pariſh? I paſſe by many things: patience, which paſſeth ouer the miſeries of priſon, with ſuch manner of delicacies &amp; ſtore, that Quailes are no meat with them? chaſtitie, which placing all perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in wedlocke, is found many times not to ſtay there? Charitie, modeſtie, puritie, they are but names, as <hi>Brutus</hi> complained when he was a-dying, that vertue her ſelf was no better; and <hi>ſacrifice</hi> hath turned <hi>mercie</hi> quite out of doores. Why doth <hi>Coniah</hi> breake downe my Cedar worke (ſaith almightie God in <hi>Jeremie</hi>) and then paint it ouer with vermillion? ſo why do the faire ſhewes of worſhip, and the firſt table, gild ouer the monſtrous breaches of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond? But I ſtand vpon thornes, while I ſtand vpon compariſons. <hi>Nos nec pugnas narramus nec cicatrices nostras,</hi> though <hi>Thraſo</hi> may; it is enough for vs, if wee may be found one day a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, <hi>Jn quorum ore no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> est inuentus do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> in whoſe mouth there was found no guile, that is as Saint <hi>Austine</hi> ſweetely expounds it, which confeſſed meekelie that they were ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:8954:38"/>and built their glory vpon humility: So much of their life.</p>
               <p>Followes their Learning: which if <hi>Quinti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> might haue had his wiſh, <hi>Soli vt artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces de artibus iudicarent,</hi> that the people ſhould not preſume to iudge of faculties, they woulde not once haue dared ſo much as to mention: They beeing ſo farre off from at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to the firſt three, as I may call it, or to anie ſuperlatiue perfection in that kinde, that they haue deuiſed manie wayes how to ridde the VVorld of ſuch a comberſome employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as cunning is; and put all their commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations in this, If they could put all Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning quite out of countenance.</p>
               <p>VVho of vs knowes not, what they haue done in Schooles for payring and nimming of the Arts, till they haue made them more bare than the King of <hi>Ammon</hi> ſent <hi>Dauids</hi> meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers awaie, and grubd not onely their beards but their chinnes? And who of you know not, how they haue declamed againſt them in pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits, as if the Captiue Woman were to bee ſlaine and not to bee ſhome, as if AGAR ſtoode ABRAHAM in no vſe for procreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and all Philoſophie were now but coſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage? Let vs belieue that they can haue rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:8954:38"/>to the toppe, that ſcorned to climbe by the middle ſtaires: let vs belieue that they are ſuch mightie men in Diuinitie, that profeſſe not onely ſtrangeneſſe, but warre to philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy. Thogh, who ſees not what a diuinity they haue coined vs? more ignorant, or more pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulant I can hardly ſaie whether. Once; they will teach their Nurſe to ſucke, with ſhame en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ough, and correct <hi>Magnificat</hi> afore they know <hi>quid ſignificat,</hi> a Prouerbe ſo fit, as if it had been made by them: while they impute thoſe errors to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> both in their teachings, and in their writings, as is a tickling to the aduerſaries to heare counted for errors; to vs not ſo lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>table to be charged by them, as charged for thoſe things, or not ſo much for thoſe things as by thoſe men for thoſe things, while the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon enemie ſtands by and laughs. And if it were not in a Theater of ſuch conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuity, where whatſoer is ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one way, is ſure to be detorted, and wreſted another way, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after as is the humor of the Conſterer; I would not ſticke to ſaie it, that they haue more er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours in their doctrine, than they haue haires on their head: and Saint PAVLS verdite is heerein alſo vereſied of them, that he that conſenteth not, but teacheth otherwiſe, knows
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:8954:39"/>nothing, nothing, at leaſt as hee ſhould doe. A iuſt iudgment of God to light vpon them, that thought it nothing worth to be counted wiſe, vnleſſe all the world were fooles beſides: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as wee ſtande not ſo much now to boaſt our ſelues, as to keep off ſcand all from the Church of Chriſt, and ſlaunder from the armie of the liuing GOD; which hath not her better vnder the <hi>ſunne</hi> (let not enuie heare mee) for all the glory of Arts &amp; Sciences, howſoeuer theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milaunces and theſe Dwarfs (only big in their owne conceipts) proudly defie her.</p>
               <p>But to finiſh this point, and to graunt them their asking for this once; let them bee as wiſe as all the children of the Eaſt, as <hi>Hethan,</hi> as <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>col,</hi> as <hi>Derda,</hi> or as <hi>Daniel;</hi> yet what get they by it, what gaine they by it, to the purpoſe now in hand? The ſtronger wit the ſtronger heretike, ſaid <hi>Vincentius</hi> of old, &amp; <hi>Origen</hi> proued it true by his exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple Neuer mean parts ſet trayterous plots abroach, neither in church againſt Chriſt, nor againſt King in the common-wealth. Were not <hi>Core, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> the 3. reſiſters of <hi>Moſes</hi> their Gouernour (as theſe are of the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, at this day) the famoſeſt &amp; the emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenteſt men in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregation? I am ſure the Text ſaies ſo. And let no man think I doe them
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:8954:39"/>wrong to rank them with <hi>Core,</hi> or his fellovv-conſpirators: For as I haue often ſaid, ſo <hi>J</hi> will ſay it once more, that as for the ſin of <hi>Core</hi> and theſe mens, but a paire of ſheeres vvent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween. Wherfore, once again, let me enforce S. <hi>Pauls Jf any;</hi> if any, be he who he will be; and let <hi>Saul</hi> take heed how he ſpare <hi>Agag</hi> for pretexts, and ſlay &amp;c. when all are a like faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and liable to cenſure. So much alſo haue I ſpoken vnto their learning, with no other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent (God is my witneſs) <hi>quàm vt iſta ilia quae ſunt inflat a rumpantur,</hi> then to prick the blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and let out the winde.</p>
               <p>The 3. point only remains; their labor, their diligence, &amp; their trauel. Wherin I will vſe no diſſembling, nor hafting: they haue bin but eue too too diligent, running with <hi>Chuzi</hi> afore they vvere ſent, and yet again, vvith <hi>Ahimaaz</hi> out running <hi>Chuzi</hi> becauſe they haue run by the vvay of the plain. A way of ſuch plainneſs moſt af them (God helpe them) as <hi>J</hi> think the like vvas neuer in vſe before, and I hope ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be in practice again. But to ſpeak to their pains: vvhat meruaile, if the children of light be not alwaies the forwardeſt in their genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? the Phariſes compaſs ſea &amp; land to make one proſelite, though they make him doubly
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:8954:40"/>more da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned than themſelues. While the good man ſleeps the enemy is not idle, but ſowes his tares very induſtriouſly. Miſchance is nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, &amp; one <hi>Ate</hi> outſtrips they ſay a hundred <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae.</hi> I could wiſh, our men would imitate their diligence; but by al means they muſt beware of their peſtilence. Who knowes not what hath bin the wonted argument of their ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s? rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling againſt our ſeruice book, &amp; defacing prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to take vp the time forſooth in preaching; like the hedge-hog that draue his Hoſt out of dores. For ſo praier lets in preaching: &amp; by it we can do, if we can do any thing. Yet as <hi>Caeſar</hi> drowned <hi>Bibulus</hi> his Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſulſhip, ſo they make one of them to liue by the ſpoile &amp; wrack of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, preaching by praying; though the Ch. be the houſe of praying nor of preaching, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſo inſtiled by God himſelfe. Then their ſquibbing at the Prelacie, yea &amp; glancing ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times at the ſoueraign authority: which I haue heard, to my great grief, with mine own ears in this Citie, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time was; not without the great applauſe of the ſeduced multitude. And now no dumb dogges I warrant you, but (which is worſe) barking afore they eſpie a thief, yea bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting true men that com in their way: whoſe legs would bee broken or their hamſtrings cut, by
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:8954:40"/>the cuſtom of old <hi>Rome,</hi> for being ſo fierce by day; wheras they are ſet to watch the night, &amp; the Capitoll to giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maintenance for ſuch a ſeruice only, &amp; no otherwiſe. They tell vs of rigor, &amp; perſecution, &amp; hard meaſure: but it is they with their tongue, not the church with hir hand, that is the perſecutor. <hi>Hagar</hi> beats <hi>Sara,</hi> &amp; not <hi>Sara Hagar,</hi> though you would think it otherwiſe whe you read the ſtory; becauſe <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar</hi> is the malepart, as hauing gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a great bel ly (theſe being ful &amp; deſirus to vent, like a veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel ſtuft with new wine, as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaies): <hi>Sara</hi> doth but as a miſtreſs ſhould (&amp; ſo the Church) ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king when ſhee is prouoked. And ſhall theſe paines bee mentioned to their praiſe, which a mean ſeuerity wil not ſerue to chaſtice? They delighted in bitterneſs, let it come vnto them; their theme was curſing, let them inherit it; be it as water vnto their bowels, and as the girdle to their loines, that they are girt withall.
<note place="margin">Preface to the chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge.</note> They tel vs, they haue laied their axe to the Prelacie to hew it down: but if it chance to ſwerue &amp; hit the ſtriker, let ſuch a man know that it coms of the Lord. This I haue ſpoken of the matter of their ſermons: but now if I ſhould enter to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat of their form, the day would fail me. Be it conceiued in a word, The moſt of them haue made Gods offerings to ſtinke, like the ſons of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:8954:41"/>
                  <hi>Eli,</hi> &amp; the pulpits to loſe much of their antient eſtimation &amp; credit, that they held in former times, by the vndiſcreet handling of their buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. <hi>Ariſtot.</hi> was wont to ſay, it was the reward of a lier not to be belieued when he told truth: ſo, many men of worth are the worſe thought on for their vnworthines. To omit other faults, ſo retchleſs &amp; ſo diſſolute they are in their prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching, that now it is become a lavv among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as it was among the <hi>Tarentines, nemo de nobis,</hi> let him be no body in the faction, that brings a ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died or a premeditate ſermon. That were to ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the H. Ghoſt to an inkhorn, turn the cock &amp; it will run well enough of it ſelfe, (I think I ſpeak their own Prouerbs:) &amp; there are ſom worſe, as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſay they bring ſermons of Gods own making, becauſe they took no pains in the pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; with others mo, that for honeſty ſake muſt be concealed. Thus they tell vs of labor, &amp; la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor, in their preaching; and when all comes to all, they hold it no preaching, if it be laborious. <hi>Alex.</hi> would be painted by none but <hi>Apelles,</hi> grauen by none but <hi>Lyſippus,</hi> one an excellent painter the other an excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t caruer: theſe can allow any to handle the word, to touch the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie with vnwaſht hands, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> as S. <hi>Baſil</hi> ſaies, baſe fellows, and (more then ſo) a
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:8954:41"/>degree belowe baſeneſs it ſelf. And therfore no maruaile, if anie thing accounted good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for our Order, when they haue coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted any body fit enough for the labour.</p>
               <p>But to let go this, becauſe they will ſaie this is to preach in the euidence of the ſpirit, and in all demonſtration of power and authoritie (though God knowes there is great difference between the two) what think you of that, that they challenge to themſelues a conuerting power, (I ſpeak no more than I know by good proof) and deny to others a conuerting mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration? In the latter whereof they are not ſo iniurious againſt charitie toward men, as in the former hainous in exceſs of pride and impiety towards God. Certainly, my deare brethren, if we could conuert others, we would firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with the conuerſion of our ſelues: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no man conuerteth himſelf; therfore, it is moſt true, he cannot conuert another. <hi>Turn vs Lord and we ſhall be turned,</hi> ſaies the Prophet himſelf, though he could preach no doubt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently: and our Sauiour likewiſe, <hi>You haue not choſen me,</hi> but <hi>I haue choſen you,</hi> ſpoken not to the multitudes but to the Apoſtles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues; aboue which leuell the Church men of our times, and the men Apoſtolique that liue
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:8954:42"/>yet, may not ſeek to ſoare by anie means. The <hi>heart of the King is the hand of God,</hi> as <hi>are the waters in the South;</hi> that we reade in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbs: but we neuer read, the heart of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is in the hand of the Miniſter to turne it which way he wil; But, <hi>Paul is nothing, and Apollos is nothing,</hi> and, <hi>We are not Lords ouer your Faith,</hi> and againe, <hi>Why gaze you at vs, as if wee by our Vertue had made this Creeple whole?</hi> Yet, as the Flie that you haue heard of, which riding vpon a coach-wheel at the games of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lympus,</hi> gaue forth that it was ſhee that made ſo glorius a duſt; ſo theſe as vainglorious, but in a higher kind, arrogate to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues the manage of that ſeruice, whereunto it is enough if they may be reputed but the meaneſt acceſſaries.</p>
               <p>And now we are not angry with them, for denying vs the fellowſhip of ſuch a preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue as cannot be helde without Gods higheſt diſhonor: but leauing them this blaſphemie to adorn their head withal, we think it worth the noting that they haue excluded vs from being ſo much as inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, aſwel as inueſted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in the principals. For, thither no doubt tendeth that ſpeech of theirs,
<note place="margin">Preface to their Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on firſt offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to his Maieſty.</note> which you may all wel remember, it was ſo famous, <hi>That all the floure is of their bolting, throughout the land,</hi> the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:8954:42"/>bran &amp; the chaffe (if anie be in the Church) is theirs that haue labour'd in a different kind fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them. <hi>Ruth</hi> could not glean ſo much as a ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, theſe mowers haue ſo carried all into their barne; &amp; the <hi>Amnons</hi> of the people could not be perſwaded to let any cakes go downe, but onely thoſe of <hi>Thamars</hi> baking. All this night haue we fiſht (may we ſay with good S. <hi>Peter</hi>) &amp; caught nothing, becauſe we have not fiſht with the worm that they haue. New <hi>Palaemons</hi> in the ſchool of diuinity, that ſay of themſelues, <hi>nobiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum nata, nobiſcu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peritura,</hi> with vs it was born, &amp; with vs it muſt die, as wiſdom ſhould do with <hi>Iobs</hi> friends. I could wiſh yet that <hi>Philip</hi> had left ſomwhat for young <hi>Alexander</hi> to conquer: but the frantike Marchant cries aloud fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the key, <hi>the ſhippes are all mine.</hi> And if one of vs do but looke out of a pulpit, preſently they haue for him, as for <hi>Paul, Quid vult hic ſemini verbius dice re?</hi> It is poſſible for a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſormer to make a good ſermon? (Let the guiltie confcience acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge his owne ſpeech) and again, as for <hi>Saul, nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quid</hi> Saul <hi>inter Prophetas?</hi> is <hi>Saul</hi> alſo among the Proph.? To who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our Apology muſt be, as then it was, <hi>Quis pater eoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> who is their father? &amp;, hath not he abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dance of ſpirit? or is all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed in your breſt? &amp;, did the word of God
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:8954:43"/>come to you only, or may it come from no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die now effectually but you? Doubtleſs, as I haue heard ſome Diuines reaſon, that they had rather be Publicans, than Phariſies, and do no good workes than grow proude or cenſorious after their dooing, which is the dangerouſeſt temptation that a man can fall into, and which moſt ſeparateth from Chriſt: So, it had been better for theſe men, to haue kept ſilence, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen from good words, than out of their labors to haue growen into ſuch a ſpirit, as either to intrude into Gods rights by ouerweening, or excluded vs as vnworthie by diſdain.</p>
               <p>Howbeit, becauſe they magnifie ſo their paines in preaching, and thinke they beare vs downe ſo mightilie that waie, wee will end this point, if firſt we deſire them, not to cenſure all ouer ſharpely that ſhall not ply the pulpit as they doo. For mine owne part, <hi>J</hi> ſay with the holy Apoſtle, <hi>vae mihi niſi Euangelizauero,</hi> wo to me vnleſſe I preach the Goſpell, and with Biſhop <hi>Jewel, ſtantem me inueniat Chriſtus &amp; praedicantem,</hi> let Chriſt finde me in the pulpit, if it be his will, when hee comes to iudgement. Yet, preaching is no neceſſary <hi>annexum</hi> of Orders (as ſhall bee defended if euer it bee doubted) but that it may yeelde to a more
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:8954:43"/>vvaighty diſpenſation; as the Pilot dooth no ſmall good in the Ship, though he ſit ſtill at the helme, ſtirre not as other Marriners and as the gally-boies ſtirre about. In a word, as <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſthenes</hi> ſaid to one of his fellow-Lawyers, that bragged he had receiued a talent for his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, tuſh foole, I had more for holding my peace; So it cannot be denied, but ſome mens ſilence profits the Church of Chriſt more than all their tonguineſſe can doe it hurt. And ſo much alſo, concerning their labours.</p>
               <p>I had verelie thought I had done with this fourth part, <hi>The indifferency of offendors;</hi> when an obiection preſented it ſelfe to my conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, which before was not thought vpon, but novv muſt be cleared in any caſe, becauſe euerie mouth is ſo full of it. For, if the green tree be thus puniſhed, why not then the drie? and if the puritan ſmart for it (ſay they) why not the papiſt much more? for ſo hath our Text, <hi>Jf any.</hi> I cannot bee ſo long as the anſwers are plentifull, &amp; yet I will point you to much in a word.</p>
               <p>One would think the Papiſt were borne like a flower, in the boſomes of vs Engliſh men, that heard theſe men take exceptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſo ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie; and again, one would think that our State
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:8954:44"/>had verie ſimple Steers-men in it, that heard theſe <hi>Phormiohs</hi> reprooue them ſo boldly. But, if the perpetuall gouernment of our Engliſh nation, ſince religion began firſt to hold vp the head, be rather a matter of wonder amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g our ſelues than of repine, of enuie to our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours than ſcandall and reproach, of thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to God, vnconceiueable, vnſpeakable, then of expoſtulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neuer ſo little; then think what credit is to be giuen to theſe exceptours, or what weight their words ought in due to ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry with them, which can find no place of enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment in our minds, til Gods mercies be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derualued, our nations praiſe ſtained, and the very truth &amp; euidence of ſo long proceedings ſhamefully denied. As for the affairs of State, I ſhall ſpeake another time, &amp; ſhew what reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence belongs vnto them, the ark that may not be pried into, the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tain that a beaſt may not preſume to touch, the ſun that dazels curious beholders, the ſea that ſwallows profane ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turers, the waie of an Eagle in the aire, and the waie of a Shippe in the waters, whoſe tracte may not be eſpied nor enquired, but admired and adored a-farre of. For euen of them hath God pronounced an <hi>O homo, tu quis es?</hi> and none may ſay vnto a king, <hi>Cur ſic facis?</hi> Why
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:8954:44"/>doeſt thou ſo? <hi>Eccleſiaſt.</hi> 8.4. or to the Princes, <hi>you are vniuſt,</hi> as <hi>Job</hi> hath it: Leaſt of all they, that knovv not ſo much as the vvaie into the Citty, ſaies <hi>Salomon,</hi> but leeſe themſelues in ſeeking for their own Fathers houſe; a houſe, vvhich, of all other houſes, might vvell be the moſt conſpicuous to them at this daie, the Church of God in their own Land.</p>
               <p>And how then, if the Magiſtrate, vpon great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiderations, ſhould alter his hand in procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding againſt papiſts, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> doth change his voice among the <hi>Galath?</hi> how if he ſhould turn ſternneſſe into mildneſſe, as before mildneſſe gaue place to ſternneſs; <hi>ſuſpendens verbera,</hi> and <hi>producens vbera,</hi> as the Fathers ſpeake, &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring ſuffuſion of bloude before effuſion, ſhame before ſmart with <hi>Tertullian?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Petilianus a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> pud Augus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Sith this is moſt certaine that not onely <hi>Chriſtianitas</hi> (as that author ſaied) but euen <hi>haereſis mortibus creſcit,</hi> the more they are pruned the more they grovve; and vvhome the horror of their ovvne late vnnaturall proceedings, ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie illuſtrated vvith the Commentaries of our patience, cannot reade a Lecture to, of a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter minde, them no bondage nor harde mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure can euer be thought able to ſuppreſse or reclaime.</p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:8954:45"/>
               <p> This I might ſaie in defence of the State, if it had been partiall, and to this I might alleage that out of the pſalme; <hi>Jf it had been mine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie J could haue borne it, but now my fellowe &amp; mine owne familiar friend, that walked, that tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, &amp; tooke ſweete counſell together, &amp;c.</hi> Could this be paſſed ouer vvithout a checke? Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, the truth is, and experience ſheweth to them that haue but half an eie, that the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts (God be thanked) enioie no ſuch impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie among vs, and Iuſtice hath not let fall the ballance, nor Cenſure yet put vp her ſword. Jndeed they are not taxed with the ſame kinds of puniſhments, becauſe they are not capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of being ſo puniſhed, as thoſe to whome more fauour hath been alwaies ſhewed. They are not ſilenced; for they neuer had bin licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to preach among vs; they are not depriued nor put beſides their benefices; for they vvere neuer ſuffered to enioie any. But in the mean time, they are ſo curbed and ſo reſtrained (as truly fit is) that if the troubles and incommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities of the two factions popiſh and puritane were laied vpon a heap, and euery man allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſhare equall, <hi>J</hi> doubt not but the puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanes would greatly refuſe it. Jt vvas time the vvheele of adminiſtration ſhould turne about,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:8954:45"/>and the Law begin to pricke them a little, that had not felt it, but laught at it a long time, and through conniuence ſlid into contempt. If it had come any later, the euill had beene almoſt vnredreſſable, and euen now wee may ſay to the moſt of them, as Chriſt did to the man of <hi>Betheſda,</hi> that had layne diſeaſed 38. yeares, <hi>Viſne ſanari,</hi> wilt thou be reformed, yea or no? The ſhort of it is, my deere brethren, though the Papiſts bee troubleſome, yet the Puritans muſt not looke to goe vncontrolled. As whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the enemies aſſault a Citie or a Town, the children may not be allowed to keep what rule they will in the houſe in the meane time, but rather liue ſo much the more orderlie. Or elſe we ſhal think there is a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>federacie, &amp; that they reape more aduantage by the thriuing of Poperie, then they pretend for, and fauour the ſpreading of <hi>Antichrists</hi> Kingdome with all their heart, if the tyrannie of the one be the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of the other, and as they ſhall haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, ſo theſe muſt be excuſed.</p>
               <p>To conclude, I might vrge them with this <hi>dilemma;</hi> If the Papiſts be not ſo bad as they make ſhew for, when they exaggerate their peſtilence ſo much aboue their owne; why are they ſo eager to haue them puniſhed? and
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:8954:46"/>if they be ſo bad, what praiſe is it for them, or why doe they place their defence in that, that they come ſomewhat ſhort of enormious Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactors? So much may ſerue to haue ſpoken to that obiection: and ſo much alſo generally of the parties indifferencie.</p>
               <p>You would not think how glad I am, hauing paſſed theſe rockes, and eſcaped theſe quicke ſands. Now we ſhall ſaile in a gentle ſtreame: now we ſhal goe forward with tide and winde. Or rather once againe beholde a whirlpoole. For, the fift part followes, which is the <hi>Cenſure,</hi> full of dangerous and deuouring waters, <hi>Hee is puft vp, he knowes nothing, he languiſheth about queſtions, of which commeth enuie, ſtrife, raylings, euill ſurmiſes, &amp;c.</hi> Almoſt there is no bottome in it. Is the ſixt any better then <hi>(the Inhibition, or the Caution) from ſuch ſeparate thy ſelfe?</hi> We might ſpeake heere <hi>J</hi> confeſſe of excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation adminiſtred by one perſon, as by <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie</hi> himſelfe. For, this in effect is nothing elſe. Wee might ſpeake of certaine ſeparators and ſtragglers from vs heere at home, erecting Church againſt Church, Altar againſt Altar, <hi>Paul</hi> againſt <hi>Peter,</hi> and Chriſt againſt <hi>Jeſus,</hi> inſomuch as they call themſelues <hi>the brethren of the ſeparation,</hi> and openlie delight now in
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:8954:46"/>that title; though in truth they deſerue that wee ſhould ſeparate firſt from them. Wee might in one word encreaſe the puniſhment by handling the two latter parts, as wee haue layed open the fault by diſcourſing the foure former. But <hi>J</hi> am not wont to inſult ouer their infirmittes more then needes <hi>J</hi> muſt, whoſe errours and euill courſes <hi>J</hi> cannot chooſe but pitie from my verie heart. One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie I had thought to haue giuen a touch tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching languiſhing away, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> heere calls it, and hanging their Harpes vpon the wilfull trees, that might make good melodie to the recouering of ſoules, if they would applie them rightly, and welcomming home of the prodigall ſonne againe.</p>
               <p>For, let them not tell vs, they would doe it, but for conditions: It is too nice in them of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, not to reach the cup, but after a ſeruice of their own; vvhen we that are ready to periſh for thirſt, are content to drink the wine out of any hand. Remember, I pray you, the Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of <hi>Dauid</hi> ouer <hi>Abner</hi> being ſlaine, and ſee if it fitte not more than ordinarie to our purpoſe. Howe died <hi>Abner,</hi> ſayes <hi>Dauid,</hi> howe died hee? his handes vvere not bound, nor his feete tyed vvith ſetters
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:8954:47"/>of braſſe, and yet he fell down at the foot of the Conquerour Yeſterday a man, to day a coarſe. No body compelled him, no body conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him, no body forced him, but his owne will was his owne ouerthrowe, his owne out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his owne vndoing, and the battell was fought betweene him and himſelfe. What wilt thou anſwer to the Lord in that day, what ſhall thy excuſe bee to him, for ſlacking thy hand, which thou hadſt put ſo manfully vnto the plough, and ſmothering the talent that he lent thee of his good grace, not in a napkin of vnprofitable modeſtie, but (which is worſe) in ſnuffe, and pelting diſcontent?</p>
               <p>Is this to ſtirre vp the gift of God that is in thee, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> bids <hi>Timothie</hi> to doe in this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle? is this to become all to all, that thou mighteſt gaine ſome? which thou ſhouldeſt do by his example; whereas thou ſtandeſt vpon ſuch ſtrictneſſe, as thou wilt bee like none but thy ſelfe. Is this not to iangle about words to no profit, but onely to the ſubuerſion of the hearers? Is this not to offende thy Chriſtian brother, which offendeſt the whole congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt, for feare of offence? Nay, is not this to be deliuered ouer, bound hand &amp; foot to perpetuall doing nothing, before the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:8954:47"/>of the laſt Iudge?</p>
               <p>Why might not thy wit be as well occupied henceforth, in explaining the ceremonies, as thy tongue hath beene violent heeretofore in traducing them? why ſhouldeſt thou not doe as much for true peace, as thou haſt done for erronious truth? what ſhame is there with wiſe men in recanting an ouerſight? or who euer liued but had his error? and, what greater con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt than in ouercomming thy ſelf? For,
<note place="margin">Lib. vlt. in Iul. Pelag.</note> 
                  <hi>Cum animoſitatem viceris qua teneris, veritatem po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teris tenere qua vinceris,</hi> as <hi>S. Austine</hi> ſaide to the loftie <hi>Julian.</hi> Yea, this were fit newes to be tolde in <hi>Gath,</hi> this would ſound terriblie in the ſtreetes of <hi>Aſhkelon,</hi> that the Engliſh nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on had voyded her faction, that <hi>Piſistratus</hi> and his ſonnes were made friends, linked in the pledge of a long deſired, and neuer to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>annulled conformitie. This, I ſay, and much more I had thought to haue ſpoken, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted againſt the wilfull languiſher of our times, the cutter off of himſelf from the ſacred Miniſterie without cauſe; <hi>That lets his daies conſume in vanitie, his yeares and beauty in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble:</hi> whoſe <hi>waters are turned into bloud, ſo that no man may drinke of their riuers, their fruite is giuen to the caterpiller, and their labours vnto
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:8954:48"/>the Graſhopper, their vines are deſtroyed with haile-ſtones, and their Mulberie trees with the froſt. Yea, the fire conſumeth their young men, and their maidens are not giuen in mariage</hi> (Imagine you by the loſſe of all their principall ſtudies and endeuours) Nay laſtly, <hi>their Priests them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues they are ſlaine,</hi> but not <hi>with the ſword, and there are no widowes</hi> (or but one at the moſt) <hi>to make lamentation.</hi> For the wretchedneſſe of the cauſe drowneth and baniſheth all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion of the caſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>BVt another theame expects my handling: which I will not ſeeke how to apply to the Text (though perhaps I could tell how, if I would) it ſelf is Text enough to the handler; And giue leaue I pray you once, for deedes to beget words amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt you, ſince ſo many words of ours haue brought forth ſo few good deedes abroad in the world.</p>
               <p>We muſt ſpeak therefore a word or two, of the worthie contributers to the performers of the dutie, that is weekely heere accompliſhed throughout the yeare, and I for my part haue now laboured to diſcharge. Firſt, the reuerend
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:8954:48"/>Father and ſomtime Biſh. of this Sea, <hi>John Ail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> (how well does it become a Cleargie man to ſtand firſt, holding out the candle of directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to others, that might in time imitate his good example? and how wel doth this charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ointment of expe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce trickling fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beard of old <hi>Aaron</hi> the high Prieſt, till it wet the very neathermoſt skirts of his cloathing?) Firſt ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as I ſaid, that reuerend Biſhop, as much eſteemed by me, as ſometimes perhaps diſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted by the world of the malepert and malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. Next the right honourable Lady <hi>Eliza.</hi> Counteſſe of <hi>Shrewsburie,</hi> that forgetting her ornaments &amp; coſtly tyres, which the Scripture ſaies a woman cannot forget (they are ſo wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and addicted to them) bequeathed her blew-ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke &amp; her purple to the decking of the Tabernacle. Laſt of all, one <hi>Thomas Ruſſell</hi> Citizen of this Citie. But I might haue ſpared that note, for the name it ſelfe was much, &amp; yet you may knowe him to bee your fellowe-Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizen by his liberall intention. The deede ſhewes the minde, the minde ſhewes the man, the man ſhewes the Cities temper and diſpoſition that hee liued in. They vvere vvont, ſayes the olde prouerbe of the Hebrevves, to aske counſell in <hi>Abel:</hi> for there
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:8954:49"/>dwelt the wits: But we may ſay, they were wont to do deeds of charitie in <hi>London;</hi> which praiſe (God be thanked) is not worne away, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth and laſteth to this day.</p>
               <p>All theſe that <hi>J</hi> haue mentioned, had this care and this reſpect, that the feet of the Saints ſhould not be vnwaſhed vvith <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally thoſe Saints that bring vvith them the glad tidings of peace, and flie vnto the vvindowes vvith their doue-like murmurings, as <hi>Eſai</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth; that the fighters of the Lords battels, ſhould bee refreſhed vvith a competencie of bread and vvine, meeting them in the halfe vvay, as <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> did; that the Prophets, and men of God, ſhould not vvant a chamber, and more than ſo, a table; and more yet, a can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſtick, not emptie of a light in it (ſaith Saint <hi>Chryſostome</hi>) but all vvell and conuenientlie furniſhed, vvith <hi>Heliſeus</hi> his hoſteſſe; that vvho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Innes ſhut out as too cutting for them, the manger might not receiue vvithout a gliſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring oblation, vvhich is Myrrhe and Frankin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe in the noſtrils of GOD, vvith the vviſe men (not ſo much vvorldly wiſe) that came from the Eaſt to vvorſhip Chriſt: Laſtly, that the keeper of the holy Paſſe-ouer ſhould not lacke for a roome to celebrate his myſteries in,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:8954:49"/>nor a beaſt to ride vpon into <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> hauing none of his own, with them that did our Lord the like fauour and curteſie; I mean they haue all prouided, that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> as the Apoſtle ſaith, that your gain ſhould not be our loſs, your profit our hinderance &amp; thankleſſe vexation both of body &amp; purſe: but they haue aduanced &amp; improoued the ſpiritualls of other men, with the loſs &amp; flinging away of their own carnalls as a gage.</p>
               <p>Let their owne vvorkes praiſe them in the gates, let their own actions riſe vp to them, &amp; call them bleſſed. Let the garments of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple bee brought forth, and ſhewed vnto the people, that theſe <hi>Dorcaſses</hi> haue wrought with their own hands for the vſe of the poore; and let them ſay to them in this wiſe, Manie haue wiſht, and many haue talked, and many haue meant charitably to this purpoſe; but you in doing it, you in effecting it, you in preuent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their ſlow and lingring determinations, haue ſurmounted them all. Chiefly, &amp; before all, let the God only wiſe, immortal, and Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, which is to be bleſſed both now and for euer, haue his due honour out of their proceedings: Who firſt gaue ſuch giftes vnto men that they might bee liberall,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:8954:50"/>and then gaue ſuch mindes to men, that out of their guiftes they were content to bee beneficiall. O how well doth his name ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding among their praiſes! O how well doo his titles amiddeſt their ſtile? and O how dead, &amp; diſmall, and diſcomfortable is all, where, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue being commended, the Welſpring of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue (which is Chriſt the Lord) is forgot to be honoured? Let him be magnified, let them be mentioned, and be you excited to the emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the like religious practice. Redeeme your ſins, cancell your bonds, break off your vnrighteouſneſs, trauerſe your inditements, defeat Gods iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, prouoke his mercies, purchaſe his rewards, enlarge your bowells of compaſſion towards all. And when you haue done all this, and all that you can doe, or all that you ſhould do, put no confidence in your own works, truſt not in your own merits, but let them be to you as droſs &amp; dongue to gain Chriſt, and the ſhining Robes of his alone in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable righteouſneſs. So ſhal your work of Charitie be accepted, ſo ſhall your labour in the Lord be recompenſed, ſo ſhal your mite be prized aboue all that is caſt in by the hand of the ſwelling Iuſticiaries, ſo ſhall the ſeede of your almes deeds ſhoot into the ripeneſs of
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:8954:50"/>a perfect blade, ſo ſhall your cup of cold wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſpring into a fountain of euerlaſting bliſs. For let no man deceiue himſelf my dear Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, the fruit of righteouſneſs is ſowen in peace of them that ſeeke peace. Heere wee end for this time.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Deſiring Almightie God, &amp;c.</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
